<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A practical discourse concerning God's love to mankind written for the satisfaction of some scrupulous persons / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21771</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12226899</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12226899</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56573</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53957)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56573)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 924:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A practical discourse concerning God's love to mankind written for the satisfaction of some scrupulous persons / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 135, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.H. for W. Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [3]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Love.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:56573:1"/>
            <p>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>matur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, R.P.D. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lond. à <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56573:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Practical Diſcourſe CONCERNING <hi>God's Love</hi> TO MANKIND.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN For the Satisfaction of ſome Scrupulous Perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> EDWARD PELLING, <hi>D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties, and Rector of</hi> Petworth <hi>in</hi> Suſſex.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>W. H.</hi> for <hi>W. Crooke</hi> at the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:56573:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>bookplate</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56573:2"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THough the Doctrine of Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, if rightly underſtood (as thoſe Decrees are ſet forth in the Scripture, with equal Conditions, and the moſt precious Promiſes annext unto them;) though, I ſay, the right Notion of them be of great Uſe, and unſpeakable Comfort to ſuch as lead Godly, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Sober Lives, yet Mistakes about them are of very dangerous conſequence, eſpecially when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe Errors riſe ſo high, as to render the ever Bleſſed God, a Stern, Arbitrary, and Cruel Being, that hath Conſigned the far greateſt part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to Eternal Torments, meerly of his own abſolute Purpoſe and Pleaſure. This naturally ſerves, not only to diſcourage People from the Practice of Vertue and Holineſs, and to make them Careleſs, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:56573:3"/>
they do well or ill (which alone is enough to prove the Falſhood of ſuch Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) but moreover to fill their Minds with Horror, and by degrees to caſt them into the very Gulph of Deſperation, unleſs they can ſcrew up their Imaginations to ſuch a lofly Pitch, as to believe themſelves to be abſolutely Elected unto Salvation, which yet is to contradict their own Principles, by pretending to underſtand a Decree, which they confeſs to be Secret.</p>
            <p>It is therefore a moſt Neceſſary work of Charity, eſpecially where ones Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is burden'd with a Cure, to teach Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſuch open, and ſuch encouraging Truths, as theſe, That the <hi>Lord is Good to All, and his tender Mercies over all his Works,</hi> Pſal. 145. 9. <hi>That God is no Reſpecter of Perſons; but in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Nation, he that feareth him and worketh Righteouſneſs, is accepted with him,</hi> Act. 10. 34, 35. That he is <hi>not willing, that any ſhould Periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 9. And <hi>that their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb facs="tcp:56573:3"/>
ſhall not be in vain in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 58.</p>
            <p>Nor are ſuch Inſtructions ever ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, as when Peoples Minds are diſq uieted and gall d with frightful appr ehenſions of God, as if he had put the generality of the World, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a fatal neceſſity of Eternal Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and that too to ſhew his Power, and without Conſideration had of their Actual Enormities. If the Caſe of ſo many Millions of Men compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively Innocent, be ſo Miſerable and Deſperate, ſuch as Reflect upon the many Sins and C mes they have in the Courſe of their Lives committed, cannot well chuſe but be poſſeſs'd with ſuch ſad and diſmal Thoughts, as directly tend to make them ſink under the preſſure of them, and to throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all hopes of Mercy; and what a wretched Condition ſuch Souls are in, none can tell but thoſe that feel it, nor indeed are they themſelves able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it ſufficiently.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56573:4"/>To prevent this intolerable Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, is the Deſign of this following Diſcourſe; which was occaſioned firſt by a long Paper, that in <hi>December</hi> laſt, came to my Hands from a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sober, Worthy Perſon in this Town, though then unknown to me. The Subſtance of it in ſhort was this, That He, and divers others of the Pariſh, had ſomewhere heard ſuch bold Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines concerning God's Decrees, as ſeemed utterly Repugnant to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodneſs, Mercy, Righteouſneſs, and Truth: That their Minds were very much diſcompos'd and troubled upon it, and therefore did earneſtly deſire me out of tenderneſs to their Souls, ſpeedily to Preach upon ſome Subject, that might eaſe their Minds, and give them ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Having Read and Conſider'd this ſerious Letter to me, I could not but hold my Self Obliged by the Duty of my Place, and in common Charity and
<pb facs="tcp:56573:4"/>
Juſtice to thoſe, whom the Providence of God hath committed to my Care, to do ſomething, that might tend towards the removing of thoſe Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Anxieties, which I perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed did diſturb and ruffle divers of them. Such inward diſcompoſures are of dangerous Conſequence, if not du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regarded in time; and though Men who underſtand the Buſineſs of a Pulpit, know very well, that general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is no fit Place for Controverſies; yet it muſt be acknowledg'd, that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Emergent Occaſions do ſometimes make it neceſſary for us to handle Points which People doubt of; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if thoſe doubts become an afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and if the Points do nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Subſtantials of Religion; and if the clearing of them maketh way for Plain and Practical things, which we ſhould always have an Eye upon, as being much better, becauſe more uſeful, in order to the great ends
<pb facs="tcp:56573:5"/>
of Chriſtianity of which kind is that weighty Point in Hand. For as long as God is believed to be truly loving unto us all, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is lookt upon as a common and conditional Saviour, all thinking Men will find great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and encouragements for them to live Godly, Righteouſly and Soberly; according to <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Laws: But if inſtead of this, People think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſure of Salvation; whatever the Quality of their Lives and Actions be, and learn the Art of relying upon particular abſolute Decrees; they muſt in the Conſequence believe, the Entire Practice of Chriſtian Morality, to be an unneceſſary matter: Talk while you will of the Eſſential Duties of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, God and Man muſt ſtand to their Courteſie for them; becauſe they think there is behind the Curtain an Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and Irreſiſtible Decree, that is on their ſide, and ſecures them from all Danger of Eternal Perdition.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56573:5"/>Beſides it is Notorious, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat among thoſe who have believed the Rigid Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Fatality, and could not work themſelves into ſuch a favourable and confident Perſwaſion of their Safety as others have done; but have Reflected upon their condition with a Melancholy Eye, as if they were under God's ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Diſpleaſure and Sentence: Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers have Proceeded to final Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by their own Hands have fallen moſt ſad Sacrifices to their Opinion; which would not have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo miſchievous, had it been Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in time.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſingle Conſiderations relating to the great Intereſt of Religion, and to the Peace and Welfare of People, did very ſtrongly induce me to Anſwer in ſome meaſure, the repeated importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties I found in the Letter I Speak of.</p>
            <p>And yet there was ſomething elſe in it which did much affect me, tho' for ſome Days, I knew not who was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor;
<pb facs="tcp:56573:6"/>
yet by the general Air of it, I perceived that the Perſon who Writ it, had a very Religious Senſe and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of God. For one thing which ſeemed to diſquiet him in a great meaſure was, how to Reconcile the Doctrine of the ſuppoſed abſolute De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees with the Honour of God; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with thoſe glorious Attributes, his-Veracity, Righteouſneſs, Goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſhine ſo very bright in the Holy Scripture, and in his Works which render him a Being Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendently adorable and lovely. This was to me an Argument of great Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and goodneſs of Mind in the Author, accompanied with a Serious Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Affection towards the Divine Majeſty. And when I came to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand who it was, and what his Circumſtances were, I had great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to believe, that the earneſt requeſt to me, proceeded from no other princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but a Religious and well governed Zeal for God's Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56573:6"/>I could not but be exceeding glad to find one of his Age and Condition, to entertain ſuch worthy Notions of his Creator, and to be ſo concern'd for his Honour, becauſe the like Inſtances are not common, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in ſome Places; and after all this, to have ſlighted a request, which I belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, could come from nothing, but a Thoughtful Mind, and a True Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Piety, would have been an Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Inexcuſable.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe Motives, I reſolved to Compoſe a little Diſcourſe concerning this Matter, though one of another Nature was juſt then under my Hand; and for my Subject, I pitch'd upon thoſe Words in St. <hi>Joh. 3. 16.</hi> a place of Scripture, which I thought was the more proper to be conſidered, becauſe the preſſing of that ſingle Text, and the Reaſoning out of it at the Famous <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Dort,</hi> had ſuch a wonderful Effect upon our Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Mr. <hi>Hales,</hi> that it quite changed his Judgment as to ſome Opinions, which he carried with him when he went thither,
<pb facs="tcp:56573:7"/>
as that Excellent Perſon Mr. <hi>Farindon</hi> aſſures us, in his Letter prefix'd to Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> his <hi>Golden Remains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of my mean Abilities, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Station, cannot hope to make ſuch Happy and Uſeful Impreſſions, as were ſo Providentially made upon the Mind of that great Man. My buſineſs lieth in a Country Pariſh, where Nice and Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtical diſputations would be loſt, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe, who are more Intelligent, and more Inquiſitive into matters of Speculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than others have Time to be. And therefore my purpoſe was, to digeſt what I had to ſay, into ſuch a plain Method and Form, as I conceived might be moſt for the Edification of People, whoſe Education cannot furniſh them with Extraordinary and Eminent capacities; eſpecially as to this ſort of Knowledge.</p>
            <p>In order to it, I thought it beſt to omit a great many things, which are Collateral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incident to this Copious Subject, and of an Abſtruſe Nature, and to ſay no more than what was juſt Neceſſary, that I
<pb facs="tcp:56573:7"/>
might contract all within as Narrow a Compaſs, as 'twas poſſible for me. And that People might not run away with No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions only (as many are very apt to do, quite Forgetting, or over-looking the Principal buſineſs) I endeavoured to render the whole Diſcourſe the more Uſeful, by making it as Practical as the ſubject Matter would allow.</p>
            <p>And firſt I did not intend this thing ſhould have gone any further than my own Pulpit, where I was deſired to Satisfie ſome Scrupulous Perſons; and that being done, I was Satisfied my Self, in having anſwered my Duty.</p>
            <p>But divers of my Pariſhioners having requested, that the Diſcourſe might be made Publick, in hopes that it may have the ſame good Effect upon others, which, They ſay it had on Them; I am the more willing to comply, becauſe ſome Heady People in theſe Parts, who are very fond of Rigid Principles, and ſeem to value themſelves upon them, have (as I am credibly told) ſcattered abroad many
<pb facs="tcp:56573:8"/>
falſe Repreſentations of the whole thing.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if what is here done, may be of good Uſe to any one Perſon in the World, I ſhall count my Labour very well beſtowed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edw. Pelling.</signed>
               <dateline>Petworth, <date>
                     <hi>Feb.</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> 1693/4.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56573:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>John III. 16.</bibl>
               <q>For God ſo Loved the World, that he gave his onely begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Interpretation of our Saviour's words, <hi>John 3. 16.</hi> What is meant by the World; and what by God's Love to the World.</head>
               <p>THESE are our Bleſſed Saviour's own words, delivered in as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and Poſitive a manner, as is poſſible for any Tongue to ſpeak; and therefore Men ſhould take all imaginable care, that they do not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wreſt, or Miſtake the true ſence of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:56573:9"/>THEY contain Two things which are moſt obſervable in them. 1. The great Principle, or Inward Cauſe that moved God to ſend his Son in the Fleſh; it was out of pure Love to the World. 2. The great End which he propoſed and deſigned thereby; it was, <hi>That whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>FOR our more profitable Inſtruction out of this portion of Scripture, Three things are neceſſary to be conſider'd in their order:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> What is the true meaning of our Saviour's words in this place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Article which they yield us:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And Laſtly, What Practical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences may be gather'd from the whole.</p>
               <p>1. FIRST, That we may rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand our Saviour's meaning, theſe two things are to be explained.</p>
               <p>1. FIRST, Who are here meant by <hi>the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56573:9"/>2. SECONDLY, In what ſence God is ſaid to have <hi>loved the World,</hi> antecedently to the coming of Chriſt, and while the World yet lay in a ſtate of ſin and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>1. SOME underſtand, by <hi>the World,</hi> onely a ſmall part of the World; a few People whom they ſuppoſe to have been ordained to Salvation by God's abſolute will, and peremptory pleaſure, without any conſideration had of their Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; the little World of the Elect, as thoſe Men are wont to expreſs it. But this is a very Falſe and Groundleſs notion; for the word is no where uſed in this ſence in all the <hi>New Testament.</hi> It never ſignifies the Veſſels of Election onely, but is always ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in a Bad ſence; for <hi>the Children of wrath;</hi> for the <hi>Evil World,</hi> as the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 4. for <hi>the World of the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as it is 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5. Uſually the word denotes all ſinful Men together in a Lump; and ſometimes it means the very worſt part of them. So ſaid <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, John 15. 18. <hi>If the World hate you, ye know that it hated me before it hated you:</hi> there it ſignifies the malicious Adverſaries of the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> and his Religion. And ſo John 17. 9. <hi>I pray not for the World:</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:56573:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56573:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56573:11"/>
there it ſignifies, Impenitent and Obſtinate Infidels. So 1 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. 12. <hi>We have received, not the Spirit of the World, but the Spirit which is of God:</hi> there it ſignifies Men of a wicked and Ungodly Temper. Again, 2 Cor. 5. 19. <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling the World to himſelf:</hi> there it ſignifies the Enemies of the ever bleſſed Being. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, 1 John 5. 19. <hi>The whole World lieth in wickedneſs:</hi> there it ſignifies abominable People, whoſe minds are ſet upon that which is evil, and that continually. Again, John 14. 17. <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>The World cannot receive the Spirit of Truth:</hi> there it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Oppugners of <hi>Christianity.</hi> And again, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 Cor. 11. 32. <hi>When we are judged, we are chastened of the Lord, that we ſhould not be condemned with the World:</hi> there it ſignifies the Sons of Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This fearful account cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be given of God's Elect; it is utterly inconſiſtent with the notion and ſtate of all ſuch; becauſe the Choſen ones of God are thoſe, and onely thoſe, who ſhew the truth and vigour of their Faith, by all holy converſation and godlineſs. Though <hi>they are in the World,</hi> yet in the Scripture-ſence, <hi>they are not of the World,</hi> but <hi>choſen out of the World,</hi> as our Saviour ſaid of his firſt Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 15. 19. And for this reaſon the World hateth them, <hi>becauſe they are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56573:11"/>
not of the World, even as Chriſt himſelf was not of the World,</hi> John 17. 14. <hi>Therefore the World knoweth them not, becauſe it know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not God, whoſe Sons they are,</hi> 1 John. 3. 1.</p>
               <p>WHEN Men meddle with points of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and eſpecially with ſuch a Tender and Weighty Point as this is, touching God's Love to Mankind, they ſhould very carefully obſerve what words really mean in the Scripture ſtyle, and ſhould form their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of things accordingly; not daring to fix upon the great Rule of our Faith a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their own, and that too quite contrary to the Sence of the Holy Spirit, as ſome have taken the Confidence to doe; whether out of Ignorance, or out of Deſign, or out of Both, God knoweth. Now, not to urge any more places of Scripture to this purpoſe, thoſe already cited are enough to ſhew, that in the Sacred Dialect, the World is taken commonly in the ſofter ſence, for Mankind in general; and many times in a ſevere conſtruction; for thoſe of them who are in the moſt deſperate condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the more wretched, ſinful, and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king part of mankind: but we never find it uſed to ſignifie a Peculiar People, Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of God, Acceptable to him, or ſo in Favour with him, as to be elected by him unto Everlaſting Glory. And ſhould theſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56573:12"/>
places of Scripture be applyed to thoſe who are ſuppoſed to be ſo elected, ſuch conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences would neceſſarily follow, as to all Rational and Sober men, would appear not onely very Abſurd, but very Impious and Horrible alſo.</p>
               <p>To come cloſe then to the matter in hand: When our Saviour ſaid, <hi>God ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the World,</hi> &amp;c. his plain meaning was, that God's ſending his onely begotten Son into the World, was an Act of his Love to the whole Race of <hi>Adam;</hi> to all men, without any exception; not onely to the <hi>Jews,</hi> but to the ſinful <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo; to all and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar that did, or ſhould live upon the face, of the whole Earth; nay, an act of Love even to thoſe who are the Ungodlieſt of the World, the moſt Corrupt People, the Greateſt Sinners, that are moſt of all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God's Wrath and Diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>2. SOME may be ready to enquire here, How the God of Purity can be ſaid to Love People that are in ſuch a ſad and wretched ſtate? why, this is the Second thing I am to conſider; and, before I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Explication thereof, I muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to obſerve, that Love and Anger are not at all Inconſiſtent. Love and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred indeed are oppoſite affections; but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56573:12"/>
Love and Diſpleaſure may go together; and very often there is Kindneſs, even where there is Indignation. As frail and infirm Beings as we our ſelves are, we find in our own Nature a mixture of theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; Thus, a Magiſtrate is angry with a Malefactor, though at the ſame time he Pitieth him. A Father is Incenſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Undutiful Child, though at the ſame time he Loves him, and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Correcteth, becauſe he bears a Tender and Entire Affection towards him. One Man is highly Diſpleaſed with another, and reckons him an Enemy, though at the ſame time he is Benevolently affected to him, as a Neighbour and a Chriſtian, and is ready to do him any Charitable Offices, as one for whom the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> was pleaſed to Die: And if theſe ſeveral Affections thus meet in us, though our Natures are Vitiated and Corrupt, How can it ſeem incredible, that at the ſame time Diſpleaſure and Love ſhould come from that Divine Being, who is abſolutely Perfect, tranſcendently Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, Infinitely, Neceſſarily, and Inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibly Good and Merciful? This being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, that I may now proceed Diſtinctly and Clearly upon this Subject; I muſt deſire you again to obſerve that there is a Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Love to be conſider'd here; or rather, a Two-fold Degree of Love; and of each
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56573:13"/>
of theſe we find in our ſelves a daily Senſe and Experiment. 1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is in our Nature, eſpecially when it is ſmooth'd and ſoftned by Religion, an inclination to do a Man good, conſider'd under the notion of a Man; though his actions towards us be ſuch, that he deſerves not thereby any kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at our hands, but rather the contrary. This Divines are wont to call, The Love of Benevolence; a Love that we bear towards all Mankind for common Humanity ſake; and an affection which the Laws of <hi>Chriſt</hi> require us to have even for our bittereſt and moſt implacable Enemies. How provoking ſoever their Practices be, Works of Mercy and Charity are due to their Nature and Perſons; ſo that we <hi>muſt bleſs them that curſe us, do good to them that hate us, and pray for them that deſpitefully uſe us and perſecute us,</hi> Matth. 5. 44. 2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> We feel in our Souls an earneſt and vehement deſire of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Kindeſt Offices we can poſſibly to thoſe that Love us again, and that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to oblige, gratifie, and ſerve us: a very Great and Tender affection, grounded on their Perſonal Qualities, and Merits, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and above that which they call for, on the account of Common Nature; and this is uſually ſtiled, A Love of Friendſhip, or Complacency. Now theſe Two Sorts, or Degrees of Affection, are aſcribed unto God, I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56573:13"/>
mean, abſtracting thoſe Paſſions and Pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations of Mind, which are ever incident to us, by reaſon of the frailty and weakneſs of our Conſtitution. That Particular, and moſt Intenſe Love, whereof there is ſome Analogy and Reſemblance in the Divine Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he expreſſeth onely to thoſe that are very Dear to him, thoſe that Love him, that Serve him with all their Soul, that Keep his Commandments, and that acquire that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Character of being his Friends; as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was called <hi>the Friend of God,</hi> James 2. 23. And the Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſaid to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>Ye are my Friends, if ye do whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I command you,</hi> John 15. 14. Hence it was, that he told them, That he Loved them, and that the Father himſelf Loved them, meaning, with a more Peculiar and Ardent Aſſection: and he told them this Reaſon for it too, becauſe they <hi>Loved him,</hi> and Believed that <hi>he came out from God,</hi> John 16. 27. For the ſame reaſon St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Epheſ. 5. 25. <hi>That Chriſt Loved the Church;</hi> that is, thoſe whoſe hearts are puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by <hi>Faith,</hi> and whoſe conſciences are purged from all <hi>dead Works, to ſerve the Living God.</hi> Thoſe Gracious Diſpoſitions, and moral Perfections, which, by the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Holy Spirit, are formed in all Honeſt, Humble, and Obedient hearts, are the onely ground of that Love I now ſpeak
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56573:14"/>
of, that Great and Abundant Kindneſs which God extends to ſuch as <hi>perfect holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the fear of God;</hi> becauſe ſuch onely are Capable of his Divine and Special Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications; ſuch onely are in a fit condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Receive them; ſuch onely are meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light.</p>
               <p>BUT yet there is a Love, which God extendeth unto others alſo; a Love of Benevolence; a Sincere, True, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Affection, which he beareth even to the Children of Diſobedience, although it be not ſo Extenſive and Unmeaſurable as that he expreſſeth to the Children of Light. He is good, and doth good unto every Man; offers happineſs unto the very worſt of men; deſires them to accept of his offers; intends to make them happy upon their hearty acceptance; and doth all things on his part, which are neceſſary and proper for a merciful God, a Wiſe and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lawgiver to do for Reaſonable and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Agents; ſo that if they periſh after all, their deſtruction is of themſelves. <hi>O that my People had hearkned unto me! that Iſrael had walked in my ways,</hi> Pſal. 81. 13. <hi>Have I any pleaſure at all that the wicked ſhould die, ſaith the Lord God?</hi> Ezek. 18. 23. <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56573:14"/>
pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his evil way and live: Turn ye, turn ye, from your evil ways; for why will ye die, O houſe of Iſrael,</hi> Ezek. 33. 11. <hi>He will have all Men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>He is long-ſuffering to us-ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 9. Theſe few places of Scripture ſpeak ſo poſitively and plainly, that unleſs men will have the Front to Queſtion the Veracity of God (which is one of his Eſſential Attributes, neceſſarily, and naturally included in the Notion of a Deity) they muſt needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that God loveth all mankind; and every one; though he be the moſt Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious and Profligate amongſt them. He hath for all a Love of Benevolence, whereby he wiſheth every ones Good, eſpecially his everlaſting Happineſs. I ſhall hereafter ſhew you, how it cometh to paſs, that God's wiſhes have not their due effect: at preſent my buſineſs is to explain the Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Divine Philanthropy; and to make it evident to ſuch as are Teachable, that more or leſs the God of Mercy and Compaſſion Loves us all, without Partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Diſcrimination. Though his Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are of a Scantier Meaſure, and a Lower Degree to ſome, who harden their own
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56573:15"/>
hearts, than they are to others, whoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions and ways pleaſe the Lord; yet to all it is a Sincere Affection, Love Unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Inexpreſſible, Unconceivable.</p>
               <p>WHEN therefore our Bleſſed Saviour ſaid, <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he gave his onely begotten Son;</hi> his meaning was, that though of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity, ſome that held the Truth, <hi>held it in Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi> others had given themſelves up to Lewdneſs and direct Apoſtaſy; and all were ſo Corrupt before God, that Divine Vengeance might juſtly have paſſed upon all; yet all their Impieties and Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions notwithſtanding, God had ſo great a Love for all, that of his meer Grace and Goodneſs he determined to do whatſoever was Needful for, and Becoming him to act, that he might Reclaim them, and bring them into the ways of Righteouſneſs and Peace; and for that end <hi>gave his onely begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56573:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Point to be inſiſted on; (<hi>viz</hi>) God's unfeigned Love to all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. Proved, Firſt, from the Command touching the Univerſal Promulgation of the Goſpel.</head>
               <p>AND now the Point which ariſeth hence, is this, That the Son of God's coming into the World, was a ſtrong Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and an evident Expreſſion of God's ſincere and boundleſs Affection to all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
               <p>FOR the clearing of this important Article, there are Two things for me to inſiſt upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Amplitude of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion which was given the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors, for the Promulgation of the Goſpel to all the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Extenſive Merit of our Holy Redeemer's Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56573:16"/>1. FIRST, The Amplitude of that Commiſſion which was given the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors, for the Promulgation of the Goſpel. The Directions given them when the Lord was ready to depart from them, according to St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Account, runs thus, <hi>Go ye and Teach all Nations, Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt: Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to obſerve all things, whatſoever I have Commanded you: And loe I am with you always, even unto the end of the World, Math.</hi> 28. 19, 20. Though by all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons here may be meant Primarily all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Purpoſe might be, that the Apoſtles ſhould begin their Preaching at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and thence Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the <hi>Jews</hi> that were diſperſed among the Heathen; yet no Nation under Heaven was to be Excluded; but from Age to Age, and from one Nation to another the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Peace were to be carried over all the Earth, until the Conſummation of all things. Therefore not the Apoſtles onely, but alſo their Succeſſors for ever were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in this Commiſſion, becauſe the Lord's Spiritual Preſence and Aſſiſtance was to be not for the Apoſtles time only, but Perpetual, to the very End of the World. Which ſhews the Univerſality of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56573:16"/>
the Divine Grace, and that the Goſpel was to be Preached every where before the cloſe of all things, that at the Day of final Account, God may Judge the whole World by Jeſus Chriſt in Righteouſneſs; according as they have obey'd or diſobey'd the Goſpel ſent unto them. Hence the Account St. <hi>Mark</hi> gives is this, <hi>Go ye into all the World, and Preach the Goſpel to every Creature, Mark</hi> 16. 15. to ſhew, that God's intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was, that no People, no not in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then part of the World, ſhould be paſſed by, <hi>But that Repentance and Remiſſion of Sins ſhould be Preached in</hi> Chriſt's <hi>Name, among all Nations, begining at</hi> Jeruſalem, as St. <hi>Luke</hi> hath it, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. 47. <hi>Accordingly the Apoſtles went forth and Preached every where,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Mark;</hi> meaning, to all <hi>People and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons within their reach;</hi> becauſe they were to be <hi>Witneſſes</hi> unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> both in <hi>Jeruſalem, and in all</hi> Judaea, <hi>and in all</hi> Samaria, <hi>and unto the uttermoſt part of the Earth,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Luke Act.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>And becauſe God Commanded all Men every where to Repent,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 17. 30. And were it needful for me to Collect Obſervations to this purpoſe, out of the Ancient Writers of the Chriſtian Church, I could ſhew you particularly, when the Apoſtles parted Solemnly from one another to Execute their Redeemer's Commiſſion; how they took their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56573:17"/>
Provinces, and went every one into the Country that was aſſign'd him; and how thoſe Apoſtolical Perſons. who were engaged in the ſame weighty Employment; ſome in the Apoſtles Days, and many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, all Travell'd into diſtant places and Territories, that the ſound of the Goſpel might go forth into all Lands, and that there might be no People, Nation, or Language, but the good News of it ſhould be heard among them. Indeed it was the great End, for which the Miraculous Gift of Tongues was poured out on the Day of Pentecoſt, and continued for ſeveral Years after; that no means of inſtructing People in any Nation might be wanting any where.</p>
               <p>NOW whence could all this come, but from the Aſtoniſhing and Tender Love of God, to a miſerable and forlorn World; and to every Generation of Men that then was, or ſhould be to the World's End? And what could be the good God's deſign in all this, but that every one ſhould come to the Knowledge of the Truth, and ſo be Converted and Live? It was the End of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt's Preaching, to give Knowledge of Salvation to his People, for the Remiſſion of their Sins, through the Tender Mercy of God, whereby the Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56573:17"/>
from on high viſited them; to give Light to them that ſate in Darkneſs, and the ſhadow of Death and to guide their Feet into the Ways of Peace, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 78, 79. The ſame was the end of our Saviour's Preaching, that all People might come unto him, and by him might have Life; becauſe <hi>God ſent not his Son into the World, to Condemn the World; but that the World through him might be Saved, Jo.</hi> 3. 17. And the very ſame was the end of the Holy Apoſtles and their Succeſſors Preaching, that they might Save that which was Loſt, and Save all to the uttermoſt; Becauſe God's deſire was to Bleſs them, <hi>in turning away every one of them from their Iniquities, Act.</hi> 3. 26. And becauſe <hi>He Commanded all Men every where to Repent, Act.</hi> 17. 30.</p>
               <p>AFTER all this, ſo expreſly and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told us in the Holy Scripture, for Men to ſay (as ſome have had the great Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to Publiſh to the World) That God hath Abſolutely, and Irrevocably conſigned the greater part of Mankind to Eternal Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; that he ſendeth his Word to them, that they may be yet more Deaf; that he ſets up a Light before them, that they may be the more Blind; that he gives them Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, that they may refuſe to be Healed; that he knocks at their Hearts, that they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56573:18"/>
may deny him Entrance; and this, that in the end, they may be all Damned, and render'd Inexcuſable. Theſe and many other the like bold Aſſertions, do fix ſuch a foul Imputation upon the Divine Being, and are ſuch an horrible Reproach to his moſt Glorious Attributes (eſpecially his Goodneſs, Holyneſs, Mercy, Juſtice and Truth) as I almoſt Tremble but to think of, and can never Wonder ſufficiently, how it could enter into the Heads and Hearts of any Chriſtians, to Conceive ſuch Abominable and Blaſphemous Notions of God, Bleſſed for ever more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>JUSTIN MARTYR</hi> tells us of ſome Princes, who have been ſo Salvage, that leaſt Axes and Gibbets ſhould be Idle, they have laid Traps and Snares in Men's Way, on purpoſe to ſport and divert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their Deſtruction. And among divers baſe things which have been told of <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> two barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Stories fall here into my Memory. One was, That having a vehement Deſire to hang ſome Virgins (becauſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Government had that Honour for Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they would not ſuffer Virgins to die after that Shameful manner) he Order'd the Common Executioner firſt to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and Deflow'r them, that then he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56573:18"/>
might have them Strangl'd with a <hi>Non-Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante</hi> to the Laws. The other Story is, That intending to Kill both the Sons of <hi>Germanicus,</hi> he uſed all poſſible means of Provoking them to Defame him, that he might have ſome Colour and Pretence for his Villainous Reſolution.</p>
               <p>MANY ſuch Scandalous Inſtances there have been of Men, who have ſo far put off all Humanity, as to thirſt for Blood, and to delight in Acts of Cruelty and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. But they have been abhorred as ſo many Botches, and plague Sores a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Man-kind: And for Men who are called by the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that moſt Perfect Being, the Father of Spirits, and the great Lover of all our Souls ſo, as if he uſed Arts to draw his Poor Creatures into Eternal Perdition, and then think to excuſe it by a fulſome Diſtinction between God's Secret (as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to one another) and his Revealed Will. This is ſuch Vileneſs and Blaſphemy, as I muſt beg all good Peoples Pardon for Offending their Ears by mentioning it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Indeed it is ſaid that God giveth ſome a Spirit of Slumber; Eyes that they ſhould not See, and Ears that they ſhould not Hear. But theſe, and the like Expreſſions, though at the firſt hearing they ſound harſh, yet
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56573:19"/>
they do not relate to any Antecedent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree or Deſire, or Work of God; but are only Declarative of the Event which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times falls out accidentally, by the juſt Judgment of God upon Obſtinate People, who harden themſelves ſo, that in the End God gives them up to themſelves, ſo that they become Stupid, Blind and Deaf. But the Original of this is their own Willful Temper and Sinful Courſes; whereby their Hearts wax groſs, and their Ears become dull of Hearing, and their Eyes they cloſe themſelves by repeated Acts of their own; as if they were afraid, leaſt at any time they ſhould See with their Eyes, and Underſtand with their Hearts, and ſhould be Converted and Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Such Phraſes import the Perverſeneſs of ſome Peoples Minds; but nothing of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny preſumed purpoſe in God, that they ſhould be Eternally Miſerable: No, far be that from the Righteous Judge of all the Earth: Let God be True, though all Men are Lyars. Where the Word of God is Preached, and People thereby are called on to Believe and Reform their Lives, the call on God's part is Serious and Unfeigned; and they that Diſobey it, will be ſeverely Puniſht at the laſt, for deſpiſing the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of God's Goodneſs. We are Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours for <hi>Chriſt</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) as though God did Beſeech you by Us; <hi>We pray you
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56573:19"/>
in Chriſt's ſtead, be ye Reconciled to God, 2 Cor.</hi> 5. 20. This is the great End of the whole Work of the Miniſtry, to make Peace between a wronged and good God, and wretched Men; that they may be everlaſtingly Happy in the Fruition of God; and if this End be not Accompliſh'd, Fooliſh and untoward People have none to blame but themſelves. In the Parable of the Sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the Fault was not in the Seeds-man, nor in the Seed, but in the Stony-ground; it is for want of an Honeſt and Good Heart, that the Devil and the World pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a Crop. In the Parable of the great Supper, the Epulator was Kind, and the Feaſt ready, and nothing hinder'd an Happy Meeting, but the Fooliſh Obſtinacy of the Gueſts that were Invited.</p>
               <p>BY theſe common and familiar Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, our Saviour was Pleaſed (in Condeſcention to the weak Capacity of his Hearers) to ſhew the Myſteries of God's Kingdom; that God is Eſſentially, and in his Nature Good; and in his Actions Good, and ſeeketh to do Good to all the Children of Men: And in order thereunto, ſendeth out his good Word into the whole World, and his Good Spirit along with it, that all the Earth may be full of Good People, and of his Glory: That they may be prepared,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56573:20"/>
and fitted to Participate of his Infinite Goodneſs and Glory in another Life: And if after all this, any come ſhort of that Glory of God, and of their own Happyneſs, that they may have no reaſon to accuſe any, but their own Perverſe and Wicked Selves. This is the real way of leaving all Men without Excuſe: They are not Inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, for not doing things which are out of their Power; or for being Miſerable when they cannot avoid it, for Impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities would excuſe all Mankind. But this renders Wicked People Inexcuſable, that Salvation is Tender'd them, and means gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them of attaining to it, and they will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully neglect the things which belong unto their Peace. This is the Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>That Light is come into the World, and Men love Darkneſs rather, becauſe their Deeds are Evil,</hi> Joh. 3. 19.</p>
               <p>AGAINST all this which hath been ſaid, to prove the Univerſality of God's Love to Mankind, from the Univerſality of that Grace, which hath been exhibited to the World, by the Preaching of the Goſpel every where, I foreſee it may be Objected,</p>
               <p>THAT the Goſpel is not yet Publiſh'd to the whole World.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56573:20"/>ARE there not divers parts of the Earth that are yet Undiſcover'd? And in thoſe we know, or have heard of, are there not multitudes of Blind and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous poor Wretches, without any Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of Chriſtianity among them? And if ſo, how then was the coming of <hi>Chriſt</hi> an Argument and Expreſſion of God's Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Love to them; and eſpecially to thoſe their Anceſtors, who ſince <hi>Chriſt's</hi> time have Dyed in a State of invincible Infidelity?</p>
               <p>TO this I preſume to ſay theſe four things.</p>
               <p>1. FIRST, That it is impoſſible for Us now, to tell where the Goſpel hath not been Preached: And conſequently, it is not a certain Principle, that neither any of the Apoſtles, nor yet any of their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, Publiſh'd it in thoſe Countries, which are unknown to us at this diſtance; or in others which are known to be addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtill to Heatheniſh Idolatries and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. How probable ſoever Mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures may be, 'tis impoſſible for them in this, as in other Caſes, to prove a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56573:21"/>2. SECONDLY, Nor can we tell but that in thoſe Regions of the World which are now Infidels, the Chriſtian Faith hath been formerly rejected upon the Preaching of it. Nothing is ſo contrary to the Perſwaſions, Cuſtoms, and Vices of Heathens, as the <hi>Chriſtian Religion;</hi> and therefore it is no Wonder if it hath not been Received by People every where. The <hi>Gergeſens</hi> deſired <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of their Coaſts. <hi>He came unto his Own, and his Own Received him not;</hi> and ſo it is no Wonder, if his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples found ill Uſage at the Hands of Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. When he ſent them out, he foreſaw that they would not find the Sons of Peace every where; and therefore he Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to leave Obſtinate People, and to ſhake off the Duſt of their Feet, as a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt them. St. <hi>Paul</hi> told ſome of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that they put the Word of God from them, and Judged themſelves unworthy of Eternal Life; <hi>And for that Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he would turn to the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 46. Nor were all among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> diſpoſed to Believe: Though the Apoſtles had generally better ſucceſs among them, than among the <hi>Jews;</hi> yet among ſome of thoſe too, they met with unconquerable Oppoſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56573:21"/>3. THIRDLY, Suppoſe ſome, whoſe Office it was to propagate the Faith, were wanting t o ſome People; either through Careleſsneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or for fear of Death and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution: This doth not Argue any want of Love in God, whoſe Intentions were, that all Men ſhould come to the knowledge of the Truth; and whoſe Commands were, that the Goſpel ſhould be Preach'd to every Creature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:56573:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Proved Secondly, from the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality of that Redemption, which was Purchaſed by our Saviour's Death.</head>
               <p>HAVING thus Proved the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Love of God towards Mankind, from the Amplitude of that Commiſſion which <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave his Apoſtles, and their Succeſſors, to Publiſh the Goſpel Univerſally, I proceed now to a farther Demonſtration of it, from the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Extenſive Merit of our Bleſſed Saviour's Death.</p>
               <p>AS to this Matter, I think fit to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe theſe two preliminary Obſervations.</p>
               <p>1. FIRST, That the Doctrine of our Univerſal Redemption by the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is Deliver'd in the Holy Scripture, in as plain, and as clear Terms, as could poſſibly have been uſed. Suppoſing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56573:22"/>
the Doctrine were Unqueſtionably True; nay, as fully in as few Words as could have been Wiſh'd, had Mankind been Empowr'd to have Penn'd the Doctrine themſelves for their own Satisfaction.</p>
               <p>HERE the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> himſelf ſaith, <hi>God ſo Loved the World, that he gave His only Begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life,</hi> Joh. 3. 16. And elſewhere it is ſaid, <hi>That God will have all Men to be Saved,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 4. <hi>That Chriſt gave himſelf a Ranſom for all,</hi> v. 6. <hi>That He is the Saviour of all Men, eſpecially of thoſe that Believe,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 10. <hi>That he Taſted Death for every Man,</hi> Heb. 2. 9. <hi>That he was Deliver'd up for us All,</hi> Rom. 8. 32. <hi>And that he is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our Sins, and not for our Sins only, but alſo for the Sins of the whole World,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 2. Theſe Expreſſions are Clear and Open to the Sence of every one in the World; nor is any Article of our Faith, Deliver'd in Terms that are freer from Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguity, or leſs liable to doubtful mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, than theſe are. The very Being of God, though the Belief of it be the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all Religion; yet it is no where more clearly Taught, nor I think, of ſett Purpoſe ſo often, and ſo Expreſly Inculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as this Principle is. For the Holy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56573:23"/>
Scriptures ſuppoſe God's Being; and tho' they be full of Declarations and Proofs of God's Attributes, his Singularity, Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Immutability, Mercy, Juſtice, and the like Divine Perfections; yet his Exiſtence and Being, Conſider'd Abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly from his other Infinite Glories, is no where (to my Remembrance) ſo Expreſly, Openly, Directly and Frequently Propoſed to our Belief, as this Truth is, <hi>That he gave his Son to die for all Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. SECONDLY, It is Obſervable, That in thoſe Places of Scripture I have now Cited, this Principle is laid down as the Ground-work, Motive, and Reaſon of ſome Important Duty, wherein all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind are concerned. Our Saviour's Words, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout God's Love to the World, were intended to Invite and Incourage all People to come unto Him, and to Believe on Him. In the next place, it is uſed as a ſtrong Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Supplications Prayers, Interceſſions and giving of Thanks to be made for all Men. Then it is laid down as a ſure Ground for our Truſting in the Living God, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all Labouring, and ſuffering Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach. Next, it is mentioned as the great Reaſon of our Univerſal Obedience to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> conſidering the High Dignity of his Perſon; though in his ſtate of Exinanition, he was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56573:23"/>
made lower than the Angels, that he might be in a Capacity to taſte Death for every Man. Next, it is propoſed as the great Motive for our Patience and Perſeverance, and confident Hope in God, amidſt all our Tryals in this World. And then it is uſed as a very powerful Reaſon to Encourage us all, to Amend our Lives in caſe we have Heinouſly Sinned; or to depend upon <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Merit and Interceſſion, for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of all our Trangreſſions.</p>
               <p>THESE two obſervable things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing throughly well conſider'd, are enough to make all Thoughtful and Teachable Men, afraid of contradicting a Principle ſo very clear in itſelf, and of ſuch vaſt importance and concernment in its Uſe. After theſe Manifeſt and Expreſs Declarations over and over, touching the Univerſal Extent of the Merit of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Death, to make a Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poly of it, for the Benefit of a <hi>Jew</hi> only; leaving all the Reſidue of Mankind, under an abſolute inevitable Neceſſity of Periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ever. What is this, but to give the Holy Scripture the Lye, and to ſhake the Minds of People in the Practice of their Duties; nay, to Deterr them from the practice of Religion, by Ruining and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the very Foundation, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignedly laid for the Building up of all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56573:24"/>
Men in Faith and Holineſs, and to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the whole Fabrick of Piety and Vertue.</p>
               <p>BUT there are ſome particular Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which ſerve to Demonſtrate and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Point in Hand, beyond (one would think) all poſſibility of Cavil; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall inſiſt upon thoſe, after a more Copious rate, omitting many others, which if Critically Enumerated, would preſently ſwell into a great Heap.</p>
               <p>AND the firſt ſhall be the Words of St. <hi>John,</hi> which indeed I mentioned before, but have not diſtinctly conſider'd; where he tells us poſitively, <hi>That</hi> Chriſt <hi>is the Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for our Sins, and not for our Sins only, but alſo for the Sins of the whole World,</hi> 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2. 2. There is no queſtion, but when he ſaith, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Propitiation for our Sins, he means his own Sins, and the Sins of others who Profeſſed Chriſtianity with him. In the firſt verſe, he calls them, <hi>His little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> which cannot but ſignifie Believers. And if we may pretend to gueſs at God's Elect, we have Reaſon to think, both the Apoſtle and thoſe he there Wrote to, to have been of that Bleſſed Number; and that St. <hi>John</hi> thought ſo too, by the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56573:24"/>
he gives of himſelf, <hi>And then truly</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>our Fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> cap. 1. 3. And again, <hi>I Write unto you little Children, becauſe your Sins are forgiven you for his Names ſake,</hi> v. 12. Much more to the ſame purpoſe he ſaith afterwards, <hi>That they had overcome the Wicked one: That they had known the Father: That the Word of God did abide in them: That they had an Unction from the Holy one: That they were the Sons of God: That they had paſſed from Death to Life.</hi> And divers other ſuch Characters he gives of them, whereby we may eaſily perceive that St. <hi>John</hi> looked upon them to be in a State of Salvation. And whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Reads his Epiſtles throughout, will find Reaſon enough by the ſtrain of them, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Divine Apoſtle, thought his own Salvation very ſecure: Now in that ſpeaking in his own Perſon, and in the Perſon of other Faithful Chriſtians, he affirmeth, <hi>Chriſt to be the Propitiation, not for their Sins only, but alſo for the Sins of the whole World:</hi> He muſt be underſtood to mean the whole World of <hi>Infidels,</hi> for there lies the Antitheſis. And the whole World being diſtinguiſhed into two great Diviſions, the Sheep and the Goats, thoſe who are the Sons of God, and thoſe who are not; and <hi>Chriſt</hi> being ſaid to be the Propitiation
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56573:25"/>
for all, we muſt conclude, that he died for more than are ſuppoſed to be Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to Eternal Life; or elſe I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, to what purpoſe St. <hi>John</hi> ſpoke thoſe Words, or what Truth or Sence they can bear, if he died for Believers only. To ſay, he is the Propitiation alſo for the ſins of the whole World (if it were not ſo) would have been Superfluous and Falſe; and therefore this ſingle Text ſhould put it out of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, <hi>That he died for all Mankind:</hi> He Paid on his part a Ranſom for All; he made on his part an Atonement for All; ſo that all were Deliver'd from a Neceſſity of Periſhing, all were put anew into a poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and capacity of being happy for ever. And if after all this, ſome will not lay hold on the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by a free and lively Faith, nor perform the Terms of a New-Covenant of Grace, which was Sealed by the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but will trample under foot the Blood of the Son of God; this is no diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to its infinite Valour, nor to his Act and Intention, but an Aggravation of their Guilt, who were put by him into a good Condition, and might have been Eternally Saved; had they not been wanting on their own part to themſelves, by willfully neglecting ſo great Salvation. This is a Plain, Eaſie, and Natural Account of St. <hi>John</hi>'s meaning: And to the ſame Effect, though in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56573:25"/>
other Words St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>That Chriſt is the Saviour of all Men, eſpecially of thoſe that Believe,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 10. This Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could not be True, nor the Diſtinction Needful, or to any purpoſe, were he not the Saviour of them that Believe not. Why ſhould the Apoſtle come off, with an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of thoſe that believe, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not his part to Save all in general, the whole Race of Mankind? He might have ſaid, who is the Saviour of the Elect, and no more, if no more had been in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Eye and Heart: His ſaying eſpecially, doth not Limit, or Reſtrain the Merits of his Death to Believers; but only reſtrains the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Merits to them, through the fault of others, who make his Blood of no effect to them, by being Unbelievers. It ſhews, that they exclude themſelves from having that Benefit by his Death, which he purchaſed for All, and intended for All, if they would Believe and Repent: None were paſſed by, by any abſolute Decree of God, or for want of Affection in the Son of God; he died for every Man with a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere purpoſe, and upon Condition, that every one would lay hold on his Croſs, and cleanſe himſelf from all Filthineſs, by the Blood of Sprinkling. Upon that Account, he is the Saviour of all Men, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for the Sins of the whole World,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56573:26"/>
as to Merit and Intention: But becauſe all do not come unto him after all, but continue ſtill in a State of Wickedneſs and Infidelity; therefore as to Efficacy, he is not ſo much their Saviour, as he is others; to all intents and purpoſes, he is a Propitiation and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, eſpecially to Believers.</p>
               <p>2. SECONDLY, For the farther Confirmation of this Point, let us hear St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 15. <hi>This is a Faithful Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and worthy of all Acceptation, that Chriſt Jeſus came into the World to Save Sinners.</hi> The ſtreſs of my Argument hence lyeth here, that the Doctrine of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is a moſt comfortable Doctrine: Not only a Truth, but a moſt acceptable Truth: a Principle that ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently recommends it ſelf to every Man, and Deſerves to be Received by every one in the World, for the ineſtimable Conſolation it carryeth along with it. Now this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily implies, and proves, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> came into the World, to make every Sinner in it, capable of Salvation in a better World, becauſe this is the onely ſubſtantial ground of that Comfort I ſpeak of; the only Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, whence we can with Reaſon, gather that Satisfaction, which makes the Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of our Redemption, worthy to be Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by us all. A Man's Soul had nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:56573:26"/>
have all poſſible ſatisfaction, touching the Reaſonableneſs of his Hopes; eſpecially, when he prepares himſelf for important Offices of Religion, or is about to Die: Then it ſtands in need of a ſolid and ſure bottom to ſupport it, and give it reſt; nor do I ſee any other ſuch grounds for reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſatisfaction, and the Comforts of a Man, as this great Truth, <hi>That Chriſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the good of all Mankind.</hi> Though ſome are ready to flee to God's Decrees for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, and to Cheriſh themſelves with a confident perſwaſion, that they were Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Salvation from Everlaſting; yet this is no ſure Foundation to build on: 'tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to take Sanctuary there, and to fly for Refuge, to the ſecret Counſels of God's Will. This is the Work of Fancy, and ſtrong Imagination; and many People may be willing to work themſelves into it, partly out of a principle of ſpiritual Pride, and partly to quiet an evil Conſcience, and heal ſome inward ſores, which a Vicious Life hath made: Nor are any ſo ready to run to God's Decrees, as immoral People, whoſe Sins purſue them with a great Cry. Alaſs! it is impoſſible for any of us, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out immediate Revelation (which is not afforded now) to Read our Names in the Book of Eternity, or to know Infallibly that they are there; thoſe ſecret things belong
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56573:27"/>
unto the Lord our God; by us they are Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable, and paſt finding out, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we cannot gather any reaſonable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts that Way.</p>
               <p>NOR Indeed doth the Revealed Will of God (the Holy Scriptures themſelves) afford us much, without that moſt accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Doctrine, which I am now defending: For neither in this Book can any of us find our Names Written, no more than in the Volum of God's Decrees. The Scripture is ſilent as to the ſtate of particular Perſons, and all the Comfort any ſingle Man can gather from it, comes by making reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble concluſions as to himſelf, out of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Premiſes. There are in the Bible ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny neceſſary Laws preſcribed, and many excellent promiſes given to the Faithful, indefinitely and at large, and when a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon compares his private ſtate with the common Rule, and upon a due compariſon diſcovers, that according to his Power, he hath ſincerely and honeſtly obſerved God's Commands, or doth now do ſo, and reſolves ſtedfaſtly by God's Grace to perſevere to the end in ſo doing; he may then very reaſonably Hope, and Cheriſh himſelf with an Humble Modeſt Confidence, that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he ſhall be Happy. Yet all this is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſuppoſition, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> Died for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56573:27"/>
him, for if <hi>Chriſt</hi> be not a propitiation for his Sins, ſuch a Man is loſt and utterly undone, notwithſtanding all his performances. And how I pray, can any particular Man be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably aſſur'd of that, but by being aſſur'd firſt, <hi>That Chriſt taſted Death for every Man:</hi> This general Truth being believed, <hi>That Chriſt was a Sacrifice for all Mankind;</hi> and for the whole World, it is eaſy and neceſſary for that particular Perſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> was a Sacrifice even for him; becauſe he is one of Mankind, and a part of the World: But without this moſt Acceptable Principle, I cannot ſee with what Reaſon and Comfort he can conclude for himſelf; the Scripture tells him nothing of that, as to his own particular, all that he hath reaſonably to rely on is, <hi>That the Son of God Died for all.</hi> Take away this Principle, and farewel all Faith, all Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, all hope and comfort with it; I mean, all ſolid Reaſon of Hope and Comfort: Fancy and Imagination there may be in this Caſe too; but I ſpeak now of Rational Convictions and Rational Conſolation; all that muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon this bottom and foundation, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> came into the World to Die, and offer himſelf up for every Child of Man. This makes the Doctrine of our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a moſt Acceptable Doctrine indeed; a moſt Comfortable Saying, worthy of all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56573:28"/>
Men to be received; whereas without this Latitude, and as ſome People are willing through the pride of their Hearts to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, 'tis ſo far from being Acceptable unto all Men, that it ſeemeth a very Fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Doctrine. For if the Son of God Died not for all Men to the utmoſt extent, though he had paſt by but One in the whole World, and had excluded but One from having any Benefit by the propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the Croſs; that one Perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not Known nor Mentioned, how could any one of us all tell, but he was that Perſon? I might have been fearful it was my ſelf, another might have been (though with leſs Reaſon) as fearful as I; a third, as fearful too, a fourth, as fearful as the reſt; and ſo on <hi>ad infinitum:</hi> For every one in the World might have thought himſelf equally concern'd to Fear, and conſequently to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair as well as another: Every one would have been in ſuſpence and perplexity, at leaſt, as People that are forced to draw Lots for their Lives, not knowing how the chance would fall out, till the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. To be ſure, this Tormenting Doubt, would be incident to all People of ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Minds, and great numbers of very Pious People are ſuch; and then what would become of <hi>Chriſtianity?</hi> Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hereditary Weakneſs of our Nature,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56573:28"/>
the many Actual Sins we are Guilty of, and how unworthy the very beſt are of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Happineſs; what Heart or Encouragement would any one have, to undertake or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in Religion; if <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by paſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one by, had put every one thus under Fears and Dangers, of being Caſt-aways at laſt? This would have ſerved to ſpoil the whole Work of Redemption, and to have damp'd the Faith of all; at leaſt it would have brought on ſuch a Faith, as St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of in thoſe moſt Miſerable Spirits, who Believe and Tremble.</p>
               <p>I have inſiſted upon this Argument the longer, to ſhew you of what great Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence this Point is, and what weighty Reaſons we have to inculcate and urge the Belief of it: The Intereſt of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Peace of every Chriſtian's Mind depends upon it; for which cauſe, the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> hath main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it from the Beginning, to encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age all Men in the Ways of Holineſs and Vertue to the laſt. And for the ſame cauſe, our own Church holds it, and holds it out unto all; Teaching even her young Catechumens to Believe that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath Redeemed every one of them, and all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; to encourage them to all chearful Obedience to his Laws, who out of entire
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56573:29"/>
Affection to their Souls, Died for them all; and Teaching all her Children about the Altar, alſo to profeſs in the Prayer of Conſecration, that <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> made upon the Croſs (by his own Oblation of himſelf once offer'd) a Full, Perfect, and ſufficient Sacrifice; Oblation and Satisfaction for the Sins of the whole World; to fill all their Minds at that great Solemnity, with Faith, and Hope, and Comfort, and modeſt Aſſurance of finding Favour and Accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with God, for his moſt meritorious Blood and Death's Sake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SO</hi> that, it is not out of a Fondneſs of an Opinion that we Preach this Doctrine to you, though it be True; but for the ſake of a moſt comfortable Truth alſo; a Truth, that you are deeply concern'd for your own good to Believe; a Truth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all Acceptation, becauſe 'tis a ſure and ſolid bottom for your minds to reſt on, which yet it could not be, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> Died not for every Individual Soul; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>This is a Faithful Saying, and worthy of all Acceptation;</hi> Or, <hi>Worthy of all Men to be Received, That Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave Sinners;</hi> he muſt be underſtood to mean all Sinners, every poor Sinful Man and Woman, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Exception.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:56573:29"/>3. THIRDLY, If all that hath been hitherto Spoken, be not yet enough, to prove the Univerſality of our Redemption, I appeal in the third place to thoſe two A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed, <hi>That the Son of God Died, even for thoſe that Periſh.</hi> In <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. Where he diſputes againſt putting a ſtumbling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>block in anothers way, he gives this ſtrict caution, <hi>Deſtroy not him with thy Meat, for whom Chriſt Died,</hi> v. 15. And ſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 11. Where St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſcourſeth upon the ſame ſubject, he argues to the ſame effect, <hi>Through thy Knowledge, ſhall the weak Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Periſh, for whom Chriſt died?</hi> You ſee our Saviour's Love to all mankind is taken notice of, as a powerful Argument, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite our Charity to one another; that we ſhould not <hi>uſe any means to Deſtroy, whom Chriſt came to Reſcue from Deſtruction; that we ſhould do our part to ſave them, by our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive and Exemplary Converſation, becauſe Chriſt did his part, to ſave them by his own Death.</hi> This plainly ſhews the Apoſtles judgment, that though the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all, yet ſome of them <hi>might,</hi> and in probability <hi>will</hi> periſh notwithſtanding; eſpecially if others be ſo ſcandalouſly Wicked, as to lend them a helping Hand. If there be no fear of their Damnation, St. <hi>Paul's</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:56573:30"/>
Reaſoning would be vain and impertinent, and if <hi>Chriſt</hi> Died not for ſuch as are in a Periſhing Condition, St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Principle would be Falſe. After all this, ſhall any dare to ſay, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> Died for the Elect onely? Why, let us obſerve, what St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſaith to the like purpoſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>There were falſe Prophets among the People,</hi> (of old) <hi>even as there will be falſe Teachers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, who will privily bring in Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift Deſtruction.</hi> Theſe do well deſerve the Name of Reprobates and Sons of Perdition, becauſe they bring upon themſelves ſwift Deſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, by introducing damnable Hereſies, and even denying the Lord; and yet the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith manifeſtly and expreſsly, <hi>That the Lord bought them;</hi> that is, paid a Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, a price of Redemption for them.</p>
               <p>NOW to evade the force of all this, ſome take the great boldneſs to tell us, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> bought All men, and died for All men, not Intentionally, but Sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly only, meaning That his Blood and Merits were enough, and ſufficient for All<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but He did not intend, that ſome ſhould have any benefit at all, by his meritorious Paſſion. This is an Argument of great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravation of Nature, that rather than part
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56573:30"/>
with beloved Opinions, men will chooſe to put the moſt abſurd conſtruction upon the Scripture, and make it ſpeak what they pleaſe in favour of them, though they make it ſpeak contradictions. <hi>Chriſt bought thoſe that deny him,</hi> ſaith the Text: He never intended to buy them (ſay they) though he had Blood ſufficient, yet he had not the Will; and yet nevertheleſs, he was their Redeemer: Which is the ſame thing, as if they ſhould ſay, He did buy them, and He did not; wherein there is a double contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, one of the Holy Scripture, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of themſelves. An Act of Grace done by one voluntary Agent for another, doth neceſſarily include an Intention, or elſe it is not an Act of Grace. When 'tis ſaid, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 13. <hi>Greater Love hath no Man than this, for a Man to lay down his Life for his Friends:</hi> Where lies the greatneſs of ſuch Love, but in laying down ones Life with an intention to ſerve ones Friends? With a deſign and purpoſe to help them; nay, with a ſincere and vehement Deſire to do them all the Good he can? And in uſing that Compariſon, our Saviour's meaning was to inſinuate the ſingular Greatneſs of his own Love; in laying down his Life, not for Friends onely, but for Enemies; with a purpoſe and deſign, to do thoſe very Men good, that are Enemies to God, to Him,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56573:31"/>
and to their own Souls alſo; that will bring upon themſelves ſwift Deſtruction. How can He be ſaid to have bought them, if He laid not down a price for them, with an intention and purpoſe to deliver them out of the jaws of the Devil? If an Agent in <hi>Turkey</hi> depoſite a ſumm large enough to purchaſe a Thouſand Slaves out of the Hands of Infidels, but yet intends it for the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Two onely, and Ranſometh but Two, where is his kindneſs to the reſt? Or, how can he be ſaid to have bought the reſt? All that can be ſaid is, That it was in his Power to have Ranſomed All, but he did not; and therefore did it not, becauſe he did not deſign to Reſcue them. If a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtator gives a Fund ſufficient to pay all the Debts of a Multitude of Priſoners, and yet Limits all his Charity to the Uſe of One, and for the Deliverance of One onely; where is his Charity to the Common Goal? The great Numbers that remain ſtill in Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Bond, cannot call him their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, who had Abilities enough to have Redeemed them, but did not Diſcharge them, nor ever had it in his Heart or Thoughts. If a Perſon of very plentiful Fortunes, ſufficient to Relieve a whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in time of Famine; ſhall beſtow all his Kindneſs upon a ſmall Hoſpital, leaving the Neighbourhood round about to Starve
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56573:31"/>
and Periſh; where is his Compaſſion to them? How did he Relieve and Succour them? And how Ridiculous would it not be to pretend, that he Fed all, and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for all that were Hungry, becauſe he had enough to have done it if he would; enough and to ſpare, and yet would not vouchſafe ſo many Periſhing Souls, ſo much as the Crumbs that fell from his Table? To inſtance in theſe plain Caſes, is enough to clear the Point under our preſent Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. The Scripture tells us poſitively, <hi>That Chriſt Died to give himſelf a Ranſome for all, and that he bought even thoſe that deny him, and bring upon themſelves ſwift Deſtruction:</hi> Therefore he intended on his part, that all the very worſt of Men, ſhould be put into a Capacity of receiving Benefit by his Blood. If this was not his deſign, nor his Bloodſhed to that purpoſe, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with Truth be ſaid to have Bought, and Died for them, which yet the Scripture expreſly affirmeth: A Sufficiency of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, is not enough to denominate him every Man's Redeemer: That Sufficiency muſt have been given on his part, and that too with an intent, That it ſhould be a Ranſom for every Man; otherwiſe we may ſay, by parity of Reaſon, that he was the Redeemer alſo of the Devils themſelves; becauſe there was a Sufficiency as to that too: His Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56573:32"/>
were ſo Infinite, by reaſon of the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Dignity of his Perſon, that they would have ſerved them too, had God been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to accept of the Ranſom, and had <hi>Chriſt</hi> intended to lay it down for them. In ſhort, unleſs we will ſhake the very Principles of Piety, and offer direct Violence to Truth and common Reaſon, we cannot deny any People room in our Saviour's Heart; or ſhut them out of his kind pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and wiſhes; or think them deprived, by a fatal antecedent Decree, of the means and hope of Peace: The Opinion is ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Notion of the Divine Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Clemency, and ſo contrary to the Expreſs Word of God, and ſo inconſiſtent with that great Love of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Grace, that Tenderneſs of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, thoſe Riches of Goodneſs, and Bowels of Compaſſion, which appeared ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly throughout the Work of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>4. FOURTHLY, But there is one Text of Scripture more, which I have reſerved for my laſt Argument, becauſe it carryeth ſuch a clear light with it, as is enough to ſtrike any Eyes that are but open to receive it. It is the Principle ſuppoſed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as a Truth acknowledg'd, and taken for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all Faithful <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> then 2 Cor. 5
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56573:32"/>
4. we thus judge, <hi>That if one died for all, then were all dead.</hi> Where the Apoſtle's pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is to ſhew the whole World, how ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they were concern'd, to make the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> a return of the moſt Ardent and Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Affections, from the conſideration of that miſerable and loſt Condition, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into the whole World (without exception) had fallen; and wherein the whole World muſt have continued, had not <hi>Christ</hi> come to offer up his Soul for them. All were Dead, that is, in a deadly, forlorn, and undone Condition; all were concluded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Sin. The Medium to prove this Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Ruine, is taken from the Univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Redemption of the World: All were Dead, becauſe One Died for All; which ſhews, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> Taſted Death for as many as were loſt, for as many as needed a propitiation to reſtore them to Life and Happyneſs; otherwiſe the Argument would have been altogether ſhort and inconclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> had made an Atonement for God's Elect only. If one Died for a few, this indeed would have proved, that thoſe few were in a loſt Condition; but how would it have follow'd hence, that therefore all were Dead? Rather it would have follow'd, that all were not Dead, nor ſtood in need of a Redeemer, if one had not Died for the Redemption of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:56573:33"/>FROM all theſe premiſes, the Truth of the point I propoſed to conſider, will (I hope) evidently appear to thoſe, whoſe Minds are not quite Captivated to an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; that the coming of the Son of God, into the World, was a ſtrong Argument, and a plain Expreſſion of God's Sincere and boundleſs Affection to the Children of Men. Thoſe means which are neceſſary for Reaſonable and Voluntary Creatures, in order to their Happineſs, the Father of Lights, hath of his own good Pleaſure and Grace afforded Mankind in ſuch abundant meaſure, that if any People Periſh, the fault muſt be in themſelves. <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending from Heaven, was to declare thoſe Truths, which could not be diſcover'd, or made known, without Divine Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. His Cloathing himſelf with Humane Fleſh was, that he might the better Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with us, and Tranſact the Office of a Mediator, and be in a ſuitable Condition to Die at laſt for us. His Holy Life and Heavenly Doctrines, were to direct our Feet into the Ways of Peace, that he might be, not onely the Glory of his People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but a Light to Lighten the whole <hi>Gentile</hi> World. His Miracles were to ſhew the greatneſs of his Perſon, and his Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that he might be relyed on as the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56573:33"/>
ſure Hope of all the ends of the Earth. His Blood that was ſhed by his moſt bitter and dolorous Paſſion, was to ſpeak far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things than the Blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> or of all <hi>Abel</hi>'s Sacrifices. It was the Blood of Atonement to make Peace between an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended God, and a wicked World; to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Remiſſion of all Sins that were paſt, to deliver Mankind from a neceſſity of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing; and to open the ways of Mercy, to all that would deſire to enter into the Kingdom of God: It was the Blood of the New Covenant, that was confirmed upon the Croſs, to aſcertain People of all God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in it, on condition of Faith, on their Part, and of Obedience to God's Laws for the future. It was the Blood of Sprinkling, to cleanſe us from all Filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, to Purifie unto <hi>Chriſt</hi> a peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Zealous of good Works. Beſides theſe means of Grace and Salvation now menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd, God was pleas'd of his abundant Mercy, to add divers more, after our Lord's Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for the particular Application of his Son's Merits to the Soul of every Believer; that the Blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> might not be ſhed in vain, like water ſpilt upon the Ground: Great was the Company of Preachers, whoſe buſineſs was to Publiſh the Goſpel to every Creature, to proclaim the Terms of the New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covenant; to ſhew the neceſſity of repentance
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56573:34"/>
for the compleat and actual remiſſion of ſins; and to invite all Nations to turn unto the Lord, to perſwade them to ſeek and flie unto him, and to gather up thoſe Mercies, which he had purchas'd for all. And ſo the deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt was, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtrengthen the Apoſtles and their Fellow-labourers, for the Diſcharge of their great and moſt Charitable Office, but to enable all thoſe to whom they ſhould Preach, to receive with meekneſs the engrafted Word, which is able to ſave their Souls. His Gracious and Kindly Operations, are to enlighten our underſtandings, to help our Infirmities, to ſubdue our wild and unruly Affections, to confirm our Hopes, to recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our Wills in ſuch a Moral Way, as is ſuitable to voluntary Agents, and to induce our corrupt Natures with a ſuper natural Principle of Grace, for the performance of thoſe Duties which God now requires, in ſuch a meaſure as God will accept of. Thus from the beginning to the end of God's Oeconomy, there is nothing on his part but Love, Love Unſpeakable, Love Unfeigned; and after all theſe various and aſtoniſhing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of it to us all, for any of us to Revile that moſt Holy and Beneficent Being, as the cauſe of Men's Sins, as the Author of Men's Damnation, as the hater and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of Men's Souls, by pretended, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56573:34"/>
and irreſiſtible Decrees, this is ſuch a complication of Blaſphemy, Ingratitude, and other horrible Wickedneſs, as would need another Sacrifice, if that already of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd upon the Croſs, were not of Infinite Value.</p>
               <p>WERE Men poſſeſt with a true Senſe of God's Love, and his Works for us, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks nothing more would be needful to endear Religion to us, and to engage us to Piety, Charity, and Holineſs of Life: Such a mighty influence would that Senſe have over every one of our Souls, to ſtir us up to every thing that is pure, lovely, and good. And in order to it (that I may now proceed to the more practical part of this Diſcourſe) give me leave to lay before you, theſe ſix following Directions,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That you be careful to entertain in your Minds Genuine Apprehenſions of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That you do not Judge of God's Love by the Event of things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That you do not meaſure his purpoſe (as to things Eternal) by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Acts of Providence, in diſpenſing ſome ſpecial Favours here.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:56573:35"/>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That you do not think Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably of others, upon a preſumption, that you your ſelves are of the number of God's Elect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That you diligently perform thoſe things which are neceſſary, in order to the final participation of God's Love.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That you endeavour to make God all poſſible returns of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:56573:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Six Practical Inferences from this Point. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That we ſhould have Genuine Notions of God; and what Notions are ſuch.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> THAT you be careful to entertain in your Minds, Genuine Apprehenſions of God: That Wiſe and Vertuous Heathen, <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in his Book <hi>of Superſtition</hi> ſhews, That though the Fancy of an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> be a very falſe and foul imagination, and an Argument of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream blindneſs of Mind; yet ſuch a one is in a better caſe than he, who believing the Exiſtence of God, takes him neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for a Frightful, Hurtful, Tyrannical Cruel and Savage Being: And he draws a Parallel from himſelf: <q>I had (ſaid he) much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther People ſhould Report,</q> that there never was ſuch a Man living as <hi>Plutarch,</hi> than <q>that <hi>Plutarch</hi> was an inconſtant and fickle
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56573:36"/>
Man, addicted to Anger, Revengeful up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every ſlight occaſion, moved out of himſelf by little Provocations, or apt (for ordinary diſreſpects) to behave himſelf like an outrageous and unmerciful Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</q> To imagine there is no God, is to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believe; to conceive hard and unworthy Notions of God, is to Slander and Reproach him. I call thoſe hard and unworthy No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God, which are unſuitable to the Perfections of ſo excellent a Being; ſo Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious for the infinite Goodneſs, Rectitude, and Beauties of his Nature. He is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perfect in himſelf; the Supream, Chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and pureſt Good; without the leaſt mixture of any thing that is a ſtain to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; or a Debaſement and Diminution of it: This is Eſſential to the Deity, and neceſſarily included in the Notion of God. And as he is the moſt perfect Being in his own Nature, ſo is he too the cauſe and ſpring whence all thoſe Perfections are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, which are in any degree remarkable in his Creatures; eſpecially of thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, whereby all Rational Beings, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men, excell the reſt; whatever Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies are in theſe, according to the meaſure of their Capacities, we muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be in God in the higheſt degree; becauſe it is unconceivable how he can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate that to others, which he himſelf
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:56573:36"/>
hath not. Therefore in framing our Idea's of God, we muſt abſtract and lay aſide all Conceptions which include Defect, or any thing that is a Diſparagement to Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: Though it be impoſſible for us, poor Finite Creatures, to have Adequate Notions of that Infinite Being, or to Underſtand and Know him fully as he is; eſpecially while we our ſelves are in this Mortal State: Yet this is the beſt way of raiſing our Minds to the cleareſt and trueſt Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of him, by aſcribing to him, all that Argues true Excellency and Perfection; and by ſeparating from our Conceptions of him, whatever ſerves, or ſeems to Degrade, Lower, and Vilifie a moſt perfect Being. And to hit this matter rightly, we ſhould obſerve what is Vile in our ſelves, Defect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive, and Reproachful in our own Nature, and be ſure to remove and throw away all that from our Conceptions of God. For though God hath given us divers excellent Faculties, yet in each of theſe there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that doth Deprave, Vitiate, and is a Blemiſh to it. In our Underſtanding there is much Darkneſs; In our Wills there is an Averſeneſs to follow Reaſon, many times, though it be clear; a crookedneſs that makes us ſtand awry, and hold off from that which is Good; And in the loweſt Faculty of the Soul, there are many Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:56573:37"/>
and Affections, which moſt of all Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue Defect in us, and are the greateſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement and Stain to Humane Nature: Therefore they are called Vices, becauſe they are a Blemiſh and Pollution to that Spiritual Being the Soul; and ſo great a Blemiſh, that the foulneſs of them is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable, by the ordinary Light of Nature. Frowardneſs, Rage, Malice, Spitefulneſs, Lying, Inſincerity, Cruelty, Croſsneſs of Temper, Love of Miſchief, and the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſome take in Oppreſſing Hurting, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ining, Poor People; and many times too, when there is no other Reaſon for ſuch Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Actions, but onely the Fierceneſs and Violence of a Blind Paſſion: Theſe are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ugly things, and ſuch as appear very ugly in the Eyes of Heathens themſelves: They Argue great Defect and Corruption in Humane Nature, and are a Diſgrace to it; They are the Efforts of Baſe Minds, and Signs of a very Scurvy Temper; Actions that Proceed from very Degenerate Spirits, and evil Hearts; and ſuch as are hateful to all Men, whoſe Natures are at all Refin'd and Improv'd. Theſe Qualities therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo inconſiſtent with all Excellency, and ſo diametrically oppoſite to Perfection, we may be ſure, they cannot be in God; nor can any thing like them have room in his Divine and Super-excellent Nature. To
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56573:37"/>
repreſent that moſt Glorious Being as one, that from Eternity diſpoſed of Men's Lots, without any Conſideration or Foreſight of their Actions, as one that made Mankind with a ſtedfaſt Reſolution to Damn the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of them; or at leaſt, took Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by one Man's Sin, to conſign the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of his Poſterity to Everlaſting Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; To repreſent him, as one that ſeeks to compaſs his Deſign, by not onely Permitting, but Aſſiſting Men to Tranſgreſs his Holy Laws; as one that bids them Obey, and Swear he deſires they ſhould O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his Commands, and yet by his Secret Will, would not have them do it; As one that Denies, when he ſeems to offer them the Means of Obeying, refuſeth to help their Weakneſs, and yet Puniſheth them for not accepting his Help: To repreſent him as one, that thus colludes and deals hardly with his Poor Creatures; and all this, that in the end, he may ſhew his great Power over them, and ſatisfie his own abſolute and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible Will, and to pleaſe himſelf with their Everlaſting, Unſpeakable Torments; This is to Degrade God beneath his moſt perfect Self, to make him equal (if not exceed) the moſt Barbarous Tempers; to extingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh his Glory, to throw upon him the very dregs and filth which the worſt Natur'd Man is capable of; and to deſtroy thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56573:38"/>
Attributes, which are the Luſtre and Excellency of the Deity. <hi>God is Love,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; and the Genuine Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Love is, that he is ready to do his Neceſſitous Creatures (and eſpecially the Precious Souls of Men) all the Good they need. The Genuine Notion of his Juſtice is, that he evermore Acteth Righteouſly, according to the Rules of Eternal Reaſon; Rewarding every Man as his Works are, whether Good or Evil. The Genuine No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Truth is, that his Words are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable with his Purpoſe and Mind; that he cannot Lye or Diſſemble, becauſe it is Repugnant to the Excellence of his Nature. The Genuine Notion of his Power is, that he can do whatever doth not involve a Contradiction, nor Argueth Evil or Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the Agent. The Genuine No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Goodneſs is, that he is inclined to provide all the means that are neceſſary, or becoming him to provide for the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of his whole Creation, according to the Capacities and Faculties of every part of it. The Genuine Notion of his Mercy is, that he is Compaſſionate, Benign, and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent towards the moſt undeſerving Men; though by their own Faults they are Sinful, and Enemies to their own Souls. Theſe are the Glories of his Eſſence, Attributes which adorn his Nature, and which ſhew
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56573:38"/>
him to be the moſt Perfect and Excellent of all Beings. Therefore in forming our Notions and Conceptions of God, we muſt be ſure to have a conſtant Eye, and a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Regard, to theſe his adorable Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Conſtrue his Works with Reſpect to them; eſpecially the Works of his Love, which is the Attribute he ſeemeth particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly delighted with himſelf; and for that Reaſon 'tis ſaid, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>That Mercy Rejoyceth againſt Judgment:</hi> And when God was Pleaſed to ſhew his Glory to <hi>Moſes</hi> on <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> as he paſſed by before him, he Proclaimed himſelf in this Stile, <hi>The Lord, the Lord God, Merciful and Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Long-ſuffering, and abundant in Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Truth; keeping Mercy for Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, Forgiving Iniquity, and Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Sin, and that will by no means clear the Guilty,</hi> Exod. 34. 6, 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:56573:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> That we ſhould not Judge of God's Love to us, by accidental Events, which depend upon our own Choice.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> HAVING thus, according to this Deſcription, poſſeſt our Minds with True and Genuine Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of God, we muſt be careful, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That we do not Judge of his Love towards Mankind, by accidental Events, which depend upon our own choice. By accidental Events, I mean thoſe Miſeries and Puniſhments of Men, which befall them by their own fooliſh wilfulneſs, beſides God's Sincere Deſire, and Primary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions. <hi>He is not willing that any ſhould Periſh,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 9. <hi>As I Live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no Pleaſure in the Death of the Wicked,</hi> Ezek. 33. 11. And yet it appears by the laſt Words of that verſe, <hi>That the Houſe of Iſrael took a ready courſe to Die, and in Probability many of them did.</hi> Where then lieth the Cauſe of this Miſcarriage? why,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56573:39"/>
even at Wicked Men's own Doors; becauſe either they make no Uſe at all, or make a very Ill Uſe of God's Love towards them. O! <hi>Iſrael Thou haſt deſtroyed thy Self, but in Me is thine Help,</hi> ſaith the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Hoſ. 13. 9. This is the plain Account of the Matter: Help is not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on God's part, <hi>He giveth to all Men Liberally,</hi> Jam. 1. 5. He provideth Means enough to keep us all from Deſtruction, if we will ſet our Hearts to Apply them du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; he is Loving unto every Man, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man is not ſo Loving to himſelf as God is. And hence it cometh to paſs, that though God's Intentions be equally Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent, yet it happens accidentally, that they have not equal Succeſs, becauſe all do not take an equal Care to Anſwer God's Goodneſs. <hi>Some Reject</hi> (or Fruſtrate) <hi>the Counſel of God,</hi> Luk. 7. 30. Which could not be, if Mercy were not offer'd, and if God's Intentions towards them, were not Kind and Real. <hi>Some Reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Act 7. 51. Which could not be, if the Holy Ghoſt were not there to Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and ſtrive with them. <hi>Some Grieve the Good Spirit of God,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 30. Which could not be, if the Comforter were not given them firſt, to Seal and Mark them, as Men Purchaſed with the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to be his Servants. <hi>Some are in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56573:40"/>
danger of Quenching the Spirit,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5. 19. Which could not be, if the Spirit had not Kindled ſome Sparks in them. <hi>Some hide their Talents in the Ground,</hi> Mat. 25. 25. Which could not be, if a Talent were not firſt put into their Hands. <hi>Some preſently loſe out of their Hearts, the Seed of Eternal Life, others will not ſuffer it to take deep Root; and others Choak it with the Cares and Pleaſures of this Life, ſo that it bringeth no Fruit unto Perfection,</hi> Luk. 8. Which could not be, if the Seed had not been Sown: Events in this Caſe are diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, according as Men's Hearts are either Good or Bad; and according as their Care and Husbandry is, greater or leſs; and hence it is, that when all Men are called to a State of Salvation, ſome Work it out, and ſome Neglect it: One <hi>Judas</hi> continues the Servant of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath the Character of the Son of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; and <hi>Simon Peter</hi> Weeps for his own Sins, and Converts his Brethren from theirs, while <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer remains in the Gall of Bitterneſs, and the Bond of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The Reaſon of this is within Men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome are Diligent to continue and grow in the Grace of God; others Fruſtrate it, and turn it into Wantonneſs. It doth not become the Wiſdom of the great Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlatour of the World, to Drag People to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:56573:40"/>
Heaven againſt their Wills; or to force their Obedience to his Laws, by a Power that is Irreſiſtible: For this would be, to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Nature of Obedience, which ought to be Hearty, Chearful and Free; and it would take away the Reaſon of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, which Obedience cannot be capable of, if it be not an Act of Choice; no more than Machines and Engines deſerve a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, when they move as they are ſtirred, without any inward Principle of their own. God ſets before us <hi>Life and Death, Bleſſing and Curſing, and bids us chooſe Life,</hi> Deut. 30. 19. He calls upon us by his Miniſters, Word, and Spirit to conform to his Laws; he affords us all the neceſſary means of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs; he gives us a new Principle, and a Sufficiency of Spiritual Strength to help our Natural Weakneſſes, and to enable us to become New Creatures, and having ſhed abroad ſuch abundance of his Love, he leaves us in our own Power to Employ it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are Rational and Voluntary Agents, it is fit we ſhould be dealt with in a Moral way, by Inſtruction, Arguments, Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ſuch other Motives as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with our Natures; and ſuitable to Beings, which know the differences between Good and Evil; and have not onely a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of chooſing and refuſing, but are more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over deeply concern'd in Point of Duty.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:56573:41"/>
and Eternal Intereſt to chuſe the Good, and to refuſe the Evil. The Divine Grace ſerves to Help and Rectifie our Nature, but not to take away our Powers and Faculties of Acting; nor do we ceaſe to be Men, when we are called to be Chriſtians: Still we are in our own Hands in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and ſtill the Propoſals are like thoſe formerly made to <hi>Cain, If thou doſt well, ſhalt thou not be accepted? And if thou doſt not well, Sin lieth at the Door,</hi> Gen. 4. 7. If any of us fall under a Curſe, after all, as <hi>Cain</hi> did; or be Baniſht from God's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, as <hi>Cain</hi> was, it is becauſe our Hearts are Evil like his; and becauſe we throw off, (as he did) the Love of God, and of our Brother. If Men become Reprobates, it is becauſe they will be of Reprobate Minds; for God doth not deliver them up to a State of Reprobation, or to ſtrong Deluſions, <hi>So that in the end, they are Damned, till they refuſe to receive the Love of the Truth, that they might be Saved,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 10. Such Miſcarriages ought not to be imputed to the God of Truth, Purity, Mercy and Compaſſion, or to him that loved us, and gave himſelf for us: God forbid. He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to Save all to the uttermoſt, that would come unto God by him; and he did all that lay on his part to draw all to him; therefore he is the Saviour of all, though
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56573:41"/>
all are not actually ſaved. That they were to blame themſelves for, and none elſe but themſelves; becauſe, nothing was wanting in their Redeemer. He had been the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the whole World, though none had believed on him, but his Bleſſed Mother; becauſe it would have been their own Crime, if others had not believed on him, as well as ſhe, becauſe they would not have been ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered unto him, as he himſelf ſaid of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> and her Children, when he would have gather'd them as an Hen gathereth her Chickens under her wings. The <hi>Sun</hi> is truly ſaid to Enlighten the World, ſhould all Mankind ſhut their Eyes, and refuſe to behold its Rays, or hide themſelves in Holes and Caverns, from the Heat of them. So did the <hi>Son</hi> of Righteouſneſs riſe upon all; upon the Evil, and upon the Good; upon the Juſt, and upon the Unjuſt: He was Good to all Mankind, though ſome hate the Light, and will not come unto the Light, but love Darkneſs rather, becauſe their Deeds are Evil, <hi>Job.</hi> 3. 19. Now this is purely Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental, in reſpect of God's Intentions and Deſires; and therefore we may not judge of God's Love by ſuch Accidents, no more than we allow our ſelves to judge of one anothers Purpoſes and Wiſhes, by Events, that are quite beſide them; nay, contrary unto them. An upright Law-giver con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56573:42"/>
the Good of the whole Commonwealth; gives them Rules to be the Meaſures of their Actions, and encourages them all with Promiſes of Rewards upon their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and if, notwithſtanding all this, ſome will be ſo Perverſe and Headſtrong, as not to be Govern'd, but will follow ſtill ſuch irregular Courſes, as will bring ſome to the Gibbet, and others to the Flames: The Condemnation of ſuch People, is very Juſt, becauſe it is from themſelves. A tender Phyſician conſults the good of all his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, provides Remedies for them, adviſeth them to make a due Uſe of them, and tells them the danger that will attend their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful neglect; eſpecially, if the Diſeaſe be in its nature Mortal; and, if notwithſtanding all this, a ſick Man will fly in the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Face, and throw away that which he ſhould Receive; his Death is Accidental, and ought not to be charged to his account, who would have ſaved him from it. A Conſcientious Divine, I am ſure, conſults the Eternal good of all that are committed to his Charge; prayeth for them, directs them according to the beſt of his Skill and Power, calls upon them to be merciful to their own Souls, admoniſhes and intreats them, thinks no Service too much for them, ſeeks to do them good, ſincerely wiſheth their good; and, if notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56573:42"/>
this, they will not hearken, nor mind, but Deſtroy themſelves after all, by the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of their wicked Paſſions, or by their willful Stupidity; this doth not argue any want of affection in Him; it is beſides what the good Man Intends, or Deſires; that which he is Grieved and Afflicted at, the very apprehenſions of the Event is ſad, and accidental, but He himſelf is clear from the Blood of all. No Man queſtions the Affections of a Father to the Children of his Bowels; and yet it is common for Children by their own Folly and Obſtinate temper, to Ruin all their Fortunes, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Cares, Counſels, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of their Parent, and thereby bring down his Gray Hairs with Sorrow to the <hi>Grave.</hi> Now, if in theſe Caſes, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions ought not to be Meaſured by Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, much leſs are we to judge of God's Decrees and Purpoſes by any Man's Ruin; becauſe, God of his Goodneſs doth much more for us all, than what we poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are able to do for one another; how great ſoever our mutual Zeal and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be: He giveth Grace, which none of us can give; He beſtoweth his Holy Spirit, which is not in our power; He ſtrengthens us with M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght in the Inner-Man, which is out of the reach of our Hand; He Prevents, Follows, and Furthers
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56573:43"/>
Men with ſecret Operations, which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond and above our capacities to do; and if notwithſtanding all outward and inward means of Salvation, and notwithſtanding God's wiſhes to the contrary; ſome, for whom Chriſt Died, will go on ſtill in Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Sin, till they Deſtroy themſelves finally; this doth not argue any want of Love, or gracious Intentions in God, but is a ſad argument, that ſome might have been Healed and would not; an act of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs and Intractability, which in God's day will turn to their greater condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:56573:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> That we muſt not meaſure God's Purpoſes as to things Eternal, by his preſent Acts of Providence, in diſpenſing ſome ſpecial outward Favours in this Life.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> AS we muſt not judge of God's Love by accidental Events, ſo neither muſt we meaſure his Purpoſe as to things Eternal, by his preſent Acts of Providence, in diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſome ſpecial outward Favours in this Life. By ſpecial Favours, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand certain ſingular Advantages in reſpect of this World, and ſuch too, as have ſome reſpect to the World to come; in both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, very valuable Privileges and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which ſome enjoy in a greater, and better meaſure than others: And from thoſe, which I may call Temporal Privileges, though Spiritual Advantages go along
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:56573:44"/>
with them many times, to conclude that the reſt who enjoy them not in the like degree, are under God's abſolute Hatred, Or, in a State of Damnation, is very Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and Injurious to God's Honour. As for inſtance, whereas the Lord Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Abraham</hi> upon his Obediential and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Faith, that he would be a God unto him, and to his Seed after him, and that he would give them the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> for their Poſſeſſion: God intended this Promiſe ſhould be made good, not to <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> and his Poſterity (though <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Firſt Born) but to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and his Off ſpring. <hi>In Iſaac ſhall thy Seed be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> ſaid God to him, Gen. 21. 12. Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>Iſaac</hi> and his Deſcendants ſhould Inherit the Promiſe. Now this was a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Favour and Privilege to him and his Iſſue; eſpecially conſidering the Spiritual Bleſſings which went along with this Earthly one; that to them pertained with the this Adoption, the Glory (or the Ark of God, and his Glorious Preſence in it) and the Covenants, and the giving of the Law, and the Service of God, and the Promiſes of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s coming among them, and from them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 4 But though <hi>Iſaac</hi> and his Seed had theſe ſingular Advantages; we muſt not by any means conclude hence, that <hi>Iſhmael</hi> had no ſhare at all of God's Love,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:56573:44"/>
much leſs may we inferr, that he was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Rejected of God as a Rebrobate to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. For as touching a future State, the Scripture is wholly Silent, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo muſt we: And though God did not Bleſs him in this World ſo greatly and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, as he Bleſt his Brother <hi>Iſaac;</hi> yet I cannot find any reaſon to think, but that God Loved him too. For we are told, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. That God Commanded him to be Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed; which was the outward Mark of the Divine Favour, the Token of God's Covenant; and therefore we cannot ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him to have been quite ſhut out of it. Nay, God told <hi>Abraham</hi> there expreſly, <hi>v.</hi> 20. That as for <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> he had heard him, and had Bleſſed him, and would make him Fruitful, and would Multiply him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, ſo that twelve Princes, and a great Nation ſhould come out of his Loins, though God intended to Eſtabliſh his more particular Covenant, and ſpecial Favour with <hi>Iſaac.</hi> And as for <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s Poſterity, though they were not Bleſt with all thoſe outward peculiar Privileges, which <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Children enjoyed, yet we find nothing to perſwade us, but that they were allow'd to Live in the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> with their Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, if they would Profeſs the Religion, that was Eſtabliſhed there. Nay they were in a Capacity of having their ſhare (though not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:56573:45"/>
ſo great a ſhare) of the Divine Favour and Goodneſs; provided they did not turn Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, nor forſake the God of their Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> but did Worſhip him ſtill as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was wont to do, and as he Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Children, and his Houſhold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 19.</p>
               <p>I inſtance next in <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> whoſe Caſe is conſtantly urged in defence of thoſe rigid Doctrines, which are ſo inconſiſtent with the Notion of God's Love to the World. <hi>The Children being not as yet Born,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> nor having done Good or Evil, it was ſaid unto <hi>Rebecca, The Elder ſhall Serve the Younger,</hi> as is it Written, Jacob <hi>have I Loved, but</hi> Eſau <hi>have I Hated,</hi> Rom. 9. 11, 12, 13. Theſe Words ſome Interpret as if God hated <hi>Eſau,</hi> if not his Poſterity too, with a perfect ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; and by an abſolute Decree, Eternally deprived them of all Hopes of enjoying his Favour in this World, and in the other too: And hence they go on to lay down this Principle, that God hateth ſome People, meerly becauſe he will, and ſhuts them out of the Kingdom of Heaven, without any foreſight or conſideration of their Evil Works. But whoſoever ſhall with Attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Impartiality of Mind, conſider the Apoſtles meaning in that place, will
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:56573:45"/>
not find the leaſt ground for that Principle, by what he ſaith of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and that for theſe two Reaſons.</p>
               <p>1. FIRST, Becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth not mean, that God hated <hi>Eſau,</hi> in a Proper, Poſitive and Strict Sence; but only, that he did not Love him ſo much as he did his Brother <hi>Jacob.</hi> For the Word Hatred, is often taken Comparatively, for a lower and leſſer degree of affection. As the Wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>He that Spareth his Rod, Hateth his Son,</hi> Prov. 13. 24. That is, he doth not Love him ſo well as he who Chaſteneth his Son betimes. So when our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 26. <hi>If any Man come to me, and Hate not his Father, and Mother, and Wife, and Children, and Brethren, and Siſters; yea, and his own Life alſo, he cannot be my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple:</hi> This ſaying would be ſtrangely hard, were it to be underſtood in a ſtrict Sence; for Chriſtianity doth not cancel the Bonds of Nature: To Hate ſuch near Relations, is an Unnatural and Wicked thing, which we may be ſure, is utterly Forbidden by his Religion, who Commands us to Love even our Enemies. But our Lord meant, that we muſt Love Father and Mother, and Life it Self, leſs than we love <hi>Chriſt;</hi> that our Affections to theſe, muſt not compare with thoſe we are to have for him, who Loved us ſo as to Dye for us: And therefore St.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:56573:46"/>
                  <hi>Matthew</hi> renders it thus; <hi>He that Loveth Father or Mother more than Me, is not Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Me; and he that Loveth Son or Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more than Me, is not Worthy of me, St.</hi> Mat. 10. 37. In this Sence God is ſaid to have hated <hi>Eſau,</hi> meaning in compariſon of the particular kindneſs he ſhew'd unto <hi>Jacob:</hi> He Loved <hi>Jacob</hi> more, he expreſſed his Goodneſs to him in a greater Meaſure, and in an higher Degree, than he expreſt it to <hi>Eſau,</hi> though he was the Elder of the two.</p>
               <p>2. SECONDLY, This lower De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Love to <hi>Eſau,</hi> was not in reference to a Future State, but only as to ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Bleſſings and Advantages in this World. And hereof there are two plain Arguments, the one is drawn from St <hi>Paul</hi>'s own Conſtruction of the matter, (viz.) that the Elder ſhould ſerve the Younger; which can be meant of nothing but Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Servitude, according to the Will and Appointment of their Father <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſaying to <hi>Jacob, Be Lord over thy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and let thy Mother's Sons bow down to thee,</hi> Gen. 27. 29. The other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is taken from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Deſign and Drift there, which was to ſhew, that the <hi>Jew</hi>'s had no reaſon to be Scandalized, becauſe God had now given the means of Grace to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as well as he
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:56573:46"/>
had to them: Had beſtowed many Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges upon the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as well as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; had Adopted the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as formerly he had Adopted them; nay, had called the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to be his peculiar People, and Rejected them, becauſe of their Unbelief; the Apoſtle ſhews, that the <hi>Jews</hi> had no Reaſon to Stumble and be Offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at this, for this was no unjuſt or unuſual Act of the Divine Oeconomy: God did not bind himſelf to obſerve Privileges, or to conſider Precedency; witneſs his deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Iſhmael</hi> firſt, his paſſing them by, and his granting the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> to <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac,</hi> though he was the younger Brother; and witneſs his dealing alſo with <hi>Eſau,</hi> his paſſing him by too, and his continuing the former grant to <hi>Jacob,</hi> though he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the younger Brother likewiſe. Upon this Account, the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould not depend upon their Primogeniture neither: It was not an Unrighteous thing in God, to grant now the outward means of Grace, and and Privileges Evangelical to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and to make the <hi>Gentiles</hi> his peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to enjoy them in a high degree, and to take away thoſe ſingular Prerogatives, and outward Bleſſings from the <hi>Jews,</hi> though they were the Elder People. This is the plain Account of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s deſign and meaning, in the ninth Chapter to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:56573:47"/>
and all that can be reaſonably gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thence out of the inſtance of <hi>Eſau,</hi> is what I obſerved before in the inſtance of <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> namely, that God did not give him ſuch outward Advantages in this Life, as he gave his Brother <hi>Jacob,</hi> but deny'd him ſpecial Favours, for ſome Reaſons beſt known to himſelf. And in all this, there is nothing of God's laying <hi>Eſau,</hi> under the diſmal Curſe of Eternal Reprobation: There is not a Word of <hi>Eſau</hi>'s Damnation, nor any thing like it; nor do we meet with any thing (I think) in the Scriptures, ſufficient to make Men conclude, that he was a Damned Perſon. Indeed the Author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> calls him a Prophane Perſon, becauſe for one Morſel of Meat, he Sold his Birth right; to which the Kingly Power, and the Prieſtly Office, did in thoſe Days belong. But that ſingle Act is the only great Wickedneſs that is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of him, and of that, in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity he did Repent too, when he beſought his Father, to Repent of giving away the Bleſſing from him. However that was, we do not Read, that he ever Apoſtatiz'd from God, or that in the whole courſe of his Life, he deſerted the true Religion Practiſed by his Father <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and therefore there is no apparent ground, for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Sentence which is commonly paſt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:56573:47"/>
upon him by ſome, who perhaps are more prodigal of other Mens Souls, than they are careful of their own.</p>
               <p>I have inſiſted the more copiouſly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Famous inſtances, becauſe the true account of them, is not vulgarly known; and becauſe, ſome who ſhould have underſtood theſe things rightly, have quite miſapply'd them, and have argued from them to deſtroy the Belief of God's Love to the World, which is one of God's great Glories, and the great Hope of all the Ends of the Earth.</p>
               <p>AND now, to draw this point to an end; God's diſpenſing of his ſpecial Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in this Life (whether they be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd upon particular Perſons, or on whole Nations) can be no Token of their Fortunes in another Life, and therefore we muſt not Meaſure God's Love to Mankind by the Proportions or Diſproportions of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in diſtributing and ordering Affairs here. God hath a ſincere Love for the whole Race of <hi>Adam,</hi> though he be not pleaſed to give us all here the ſame equal Advantages, and in all this, God is Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, becauſe it is an Eternal Rule that we find, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 47, 48, <hi>That Servant which knew his Lords Will, and prepared not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:56573:48"/>
neither did according to his will, ſhall be beaten with many Stripes; but they that know not, and do things worthy of Stripes, ſhall be beaten with few Stripes. For unto whomſoever much is given, of him ſhall be much required; and to whom Men have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted much, of him they will ask the more.</hi> We muſt not conclude, that all People are in a Loſt condition, who do not enjoy thoſe ſingular Bleſſings which others have; eſpecially, if they make a due uſe of the Advantages which God hath given them. For theſe are things which God hath a Power and Right to diſpoſe of according to his own will and pleaſure: And, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he is pleas'd to diſpoſe of them, he doth no wrong to any. Beſides, this World is not the place for Rewards, and if ſome fall ſhort, as to theſe outward Matters here, they are capable of having an abundant compenſation made them in a Future State. But this is not their caſe, who once fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der everlaſting Condemnation; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mens Lots in another World, ought to be determin'd, not according to <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> but according to <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> Their ſad condition there, is Remedileſs, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, and the Torments they endure, are not only Simply and Infinitely Evils, but they are Evils too, which are ſuppoſed to be inflicted on them under the notion
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:56573:48"/>
of puniſhments; and therefore they muſt be in conſideration of antecedent Crimes, Knowingly and Deliberately, and of choice committed; for to Inflict Eternal Torments upon Men for what they cannot avoid, is Inconſiſtent with the Righteouſneſs of God, contrary to Eternal Reaſon, and utterly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the infinite excellency and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of his moſt Bleſſed Nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:56573:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> That we muſt not judge Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably of other People, upon a Preſumption, that we our Selves, are of the Number of thoſe, who are Elected to Everlaſting Life; and what the Scripture means by the Elect.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> CONSIDERING God's Love to the whole World, we muſt be careful not to Judge Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably of others, upon a Preſumption, that we our ſelves are of the Number of thoſe who are Elected to Everlaſting Life. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines uſually give us a Scholaſtical Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, between Election unto Glory, and Election unto Grace. By Election unto Glory, they mean God's purpoſe of bringing all thoſe, and only thoſe unto Eternal Life, who Believe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and obſerve
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:56573:49"/>
his Laws. Now though the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this be of great Comfort to all who Love the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> in Sincerity, yet the Decree it ſelf (as far as it is known to us) is General; it is Revealed to us in general Terms; as to particulars, it is ſecret: par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars are not to be known; nor can any ordinary Chriſtian be Infallibly certain, that he is choſen to Everlaſting Happineſs, till he is gone out of the World.</p>
               <p>WE Read indeed of a Book of Life, wherein Men's Names are ſaid to be Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of ſuch a Book he ſaw in his Viſion; the deſign whereof was, to repreſent things to us in a way, which was moſt adapted and ſuitable to our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities. The meaning of the Viſion as to that, is, that God doth infallibly Know, and at the Day of Judgment will openly Declare, Reveal, and Reward thoſe who do now Faithfully ſerve him; of this purpoſe of God, there is no manner of Queſtion, and therefore if Men conceive, that we diſpute againſt any ſuch Decree, they do but beat the Air, and Talk of Matters which they do not underſtand. The thing inſiſted on is this, that none are choſen to Eternal Happineſs, without any conſideration of their Faith, and Works, and perſeverance to the end in well doing.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:56573:50"/>
And as touching a Man's particular Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto Glory, or the Gracious purpoſe of God towards this or that Perſon in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; this we ſay, is a Secret, a Decree not to be known, till the Book of Life comes to be opened, that is, till the Day of Doom cometh. Therefore every one of us muſt ſtay our time, nor muſt any dare to go now upon fond preſumptions of their own; eſpecially ſo as to condemn or think hardly of others: I call ſuch partial Conceits, fond Preſumptions of Men's own, becauſe, though many People be ſtrongly perſwaded, that they are abſolutely and particularly Ordained unto Life, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not miſcarry; yet as to this, they believe without Book, and without ſufficient Grounds, becauſe they want the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Divine Revelation, which is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſure Ground-work of a right Faith. 'Tis Imagination only, and Opinion how ſtrong and violent ſoever it may be; and inſtead of being bottom'd upon the Word of God, it may proceed from two very evil Cauſes.</p>
               <p>1. FIRST, From a Spirit of Pride, which Tempteth ſome to think, their Names <hi>ought</hi> to be Written in Heaven, and therefore are ſoon perſwaded to believe, that they really <hi>are</hi> ſo, though for this,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:56573:50"/>
they take either their own Word, or the Opinion of others, whoſe Perſons they have in equal admiration. I heartily wiſh, that all ſuch as go upon this imagination, would ſeriouſly conſider, whether this be not one prime reaſon of it, becauſe it is a Notion ſo very pleaſing and ſuitable to their own Hearts.</p>
               <p>2. SECONDLY, It may proceed too from a Principle of Carnality; for it is an imagination that is Friendly and Kind to Fleſh and Blood: Where-ever it prevails ſuch as are poſſeſt withit, find no neceſſity for them to mortifie their Luſts, and to be careful of Living Godly, Righteouſs, and Sober Lives. This they call good Morality, but cannot think it of any uſe to them, becauſe they ſuppoſe themſelves ſure of their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by God's Abſoute Decree; upon this Account, they and their Vices may dwell very quietly and lovingly together: They may be Lew'd, Diſhoneſt, Unjuſt, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical, Malicious, Revengeful, Falſe, Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome, Uncharitable, Proud, and Lovers of the World; and yet theſe Vices are (as they think) conſiſtent with their State of Grace, becauſe they are perſwaded that ſtands firtm, upon the immutable Will of God. Conſidering therefore the Vanity and Origical of ſuch <hi>Phariſaical</hi> conceits,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:56573:51"/>
it is very dangerous for People to give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way to them, and more dangerous to truſt to them after a preſumptuous manner, and moſt of all dangerous to value them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon them; eſpecially ſo, as to Judge uncharitably of others, as if they were no better than Reprobates and Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aways. This is a very ill thing, and that which is far from being a Sign of their particular Election; rather indeed an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the contrary, becauſe all Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs, is a direct Violation of the Law of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by which we ſhall all of us be Judged in the Day of God. Since God Loves us all, inſtead of ſhutting any out of his Kingdom, every one ſhould lend his Brother his Hand to help him in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> FOR ſecondly there is (as Divines uſually ſpeak) an Election unto Grace, which we have all a Title unto. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection unto Grace is, when People have this great Bleſſing and Privilege given them, to Live under the means of Grace; when they have the Goſpel Myſteries Publiſh'd and Revealed to them; and when they have the Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit offer'd and afforded them ſo that they Receive the Truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus:</hi> Whatever Fancies ſome are apt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:56573:51"/>
to entertain concerning this matter; this is the true Scripture Notion of Election. Accordingly the Scripture means by the Elect of God, not ſuch as are ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have been from Eternity particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, and by name deſigned for Glory; for I can confidently ſay it, that the Word is not (in that Sence) any where uſed in the whole Scripture, but gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſuch as now profeſs true Faith in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and eſpecially ſuch Eminent Perſons among them, as by their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Holy Lives, adorn the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of God their Saviour in all things, and reſolve firmly and faithfully to Perſevere unto the end in ſo doing. The Reaſon of this honourable Appellation, is taken from the different Effect, which the Word of God hath upon the Hearts of them that hear it: On ſome it maketh a ſlight and ſuperficial Impreſſion, like the Seed caſt on the Way ſide: Others receive it with Joy, and Believe for a while; but in time of Temptation, immediately fall away: In others, it taketh deeper and better Root; but yet in time, is choaked with the Cares, and Riches, and Pleaſures of this Life, ſo that it bringeth no Fruit to Perfection. But others there are (though the feweſt in number) that lay up the Word in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:56573:52"/>
Honeſt and Good Hearts, and that bring forth Fruit plentifully, and with perſeverance in well-doing to their Lives end. Now of all that Profeſs <hi>Christ</hi>'s Religion, thoſe who adhere cloſe to it are the beſt, the moſt Eminent and Principal ones; and therefore the Scripture calleth them, after a more peculiar manner, The Elect. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are called to the knowledge of the Truth, but few are choſen, ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; or according to the <hi>Greek,</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect are few; that is, the Faithful and Choice Profeſſors of the Truth, are few in compariſon. So <hi>Matt.</hi> 24. 22. Our Saviour ſpeaking of the great Tribulation that was to come upon <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaid, <hi>That for the Elects ſake, thoſe Days ſhould be ſhorined;</hi> meaning, that out of Reſpect and Love to the true Believers among the <hi>Jews,</hi> God would ſhorten the time ſo, that a remnant even of the Unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould eſcape too, though they did not deſerve it. So again, <hi>v.</hi> 24. Our Lord foretold, that Falſe <hi>Chriſts</hi> would ariſe, which would (if it were poſſible) deceive the very Elect; that is, the moſt Sincere, Perſevering Chriſtians, to uſe the Words of our incomparable Paraphraſt Dr. <hi>Hammond.</hi> And ſo in divers other places, where it is ſaid, that God will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together his Elect; that he will A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:56573:52"/>
his own Elect; that none ſhall lay any thing to the Charge of God's Elect; that we muſt put on (as the Elect of God) Holy and Beloved Bowels of Mercy; and the like, the Word ſignifies thoſe, who are now in a Bleſſed State of Faith and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; thoſe who Serve, Obey, and Love the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> in Sincerity. Briefly if you ſearch the New Teſtament through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, you will find this Obſervation true, that generally ſpeaking, People are called the Elect of God, not in reſpect of any Antecedent particular Decree, which is a thing altogether hidden; but in reſpect of thoſe excellent Qualities, Vertues, and Perfections, for which ſome are Eminent and Exemplary in this preſent World; and becauſe for their gracious diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and endowments, they are the Choiceſt, the Beſt, the moſt valuable part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; a peculiar people, Zealous of good Works. There is no doubt but God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who are his, who will continue his, who will be fit and rightly prepared for his moſt Glorious, Beatifical Preſence. But we have no Revelation concerning of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; and as for the Scripture, which is the ſtanding Revelation we are to truſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to and to go by, it meaneth by the Elect, Sincere, Sound, Holy, and Faithful Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians: They are God's Elect, in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Sence.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:56573:53"/>AND hence it followeth, that none of thoſe People who profeſs the Faith of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and Obedience to him, ſhould be Cenſorious and Uncharitable to others, who own the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> as well as they; and who are (for ought they know) in as ready, nay by their Humility and Charity, in a readier way to Eternal Happineſs, than ſuch as out of a principle of <hi>Phariſaiſm,</hi> and Spiritual Pride, Judge hardly of their Brethren. Have they been Baptized in the Name of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> So have we: Do they Believe the ſeveral Articles of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith?</hi> So do we: Do they uſe the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> So do we: Do they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Holineſs? I pray God we may all appear Holy in the Day of God; and I wiſh ſome be not groſly miſtaken in the Notion of Holineſs: for it doth not conſiſt in a demure Look, nor in odd Geſtures, nor in dry Opinions, nor in Raptures and Ecſtacies, nor in Niceneſs, Affectation, or Singularity as to Matters Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial. But good Morality is a great part of True Holineſs, and it doth entirely conſiſt in a Godly, Righteous, and Sober Life: And whether their Holineſs or ours be moſt ſubſtantial, that Day will ſhew, when all our Works ſhall be tried, and when God will Judge even the Secrets of Men by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:56573:53"/>IN the mean time, People ſhould not talk of their Election and Holineſs, ſo as to forget Charity. God's great and undeſerved Goodneſs to us all, ſhould Teach us to be Good, and Kind, and Affectionate to each other. <hi>Beloved, if God ſo Loved us, we ought alſo to love one another,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 11. Some have a ſtrange faculty of Predeſtinating Themſelves to Eternal Happineſs, and of Reprobating others to Eternal Miſery. But by all that I have read, and conſidered upon this Subject, it is great Ignorance joyn'd together with Self-love and Factiouſneſs of Spirit, that prevails with ſome Men to maintain a Point ſo oppoſite to the Love of God, ſince the Point has been ſo accurately Examined, eſpecially in theſe Later, and more Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Ages.</p>
               <p>INSTEAD of expreſſing uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to one another, upon fond preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when we are all called by the Great Mercy of God to a State of Savlation; we ſhould every one of us give diligence, to make our Calling and Election ſure, as the Apoſtle tells us, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10. Meaning, that we ſhould make ſuch a good uſe of theſe means of Grace, we have the Privilege and Happineſs of enjoying, that they may
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:56573:54"/>
be effectual to us, and that we fail not of obtaining the end of that Faith and Hope, to which we are all called. And the way the Apoſtle directs, is Plain and Open: If (ſaith he) ye do theſe things, ye ſhall never fall; that is, if ye do the things he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth particularly at the 5, 6, and 7, <hi>ver.</hi> of that Chapter; if ye add to your Faith Vertue, and to Vertue Knowledge, and to Knowledge Temperance, and to Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Patience, and to Patience, Godlineſs, and to Godlineſs, Brotherly Kindneſs, and to Brotherly Kindneſs, Charity: If theſe things be in you, and abound, ye ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fall. You ſee the Terms of Everlaſting Life are conditional; and that it lies on our part to perform thoſe conditions. Whence it neceſſarily follows, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God's Purpoſes are, there are none on Their ſide, who are People of Ungodly and Uncharitable Minds. The Decree is extant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 14. <hi>Without Holineſs</hi> (that is, without the entire practice of Religion) <hi>no Man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> and therefore it is very dangerous, to truſt to God's Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Decrees, while Men are wanting to that which is a manifeſt Duty. Beſides, there is required Habitual Sanctity, and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Heart, to fit and prepare us for an Heavenly State; to make us Meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of Saints in
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:56573:54"/>
Light, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 2. without this gracious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Soul, the Works of Heaven would be utterly Unſuitable to our Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and we our ſelves ſhould be utterly Uncapable of exerting our faculties upon them, with the chearfulneſs and pleaſure which is the Life of the Bleſſed; and the Joys there are of ſuch a Spiritual and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime Nature, that they are altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with Tempers, which are Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Senſual, Deviliſh. So that, were there no Decree, to keep Evil-minded People out of God's Everlaſting Kingdom; the very Nature of the Thing would render it ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely impoſſible for them to be Happy in it, becauſe their Corrupt diſpoſitions are quite Unfit for it; nay, Averſe and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to thoſe things, wherein the Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heaven doth conſiſt. Therefore, inſtead of taking upon us to ſhut others out, we ſhould have a great care leſt we exclude our ſelves; by depending upon Decrees on God's part, without Holineſs on our own: Upon ſuch Decrees, as may be ſaid to be of our own making, if we do not qualifie our ſelves in ſuch a ſort as God hath commanded us. Men ſhould look very well at Home, inquire diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into their true State, Rectifie their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Mould their Hearts unto a Divine Frame, ſet their Affections on things which
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:56573:55"/>
are Honeſt, Pure, and Lovely; Reſemble God, by being Merciful and Good to All; and Imprint on their Souls, thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Characters, which are a Similitude of His Perfections, and Glory. This is the ultimate end of God's Love to us all, that he may make us like unto Himſelf, in the entire goodneſs of our Nature; and that by thoſe means he may render us tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Happy in the Fruition of Himſelf: And whatever ſome giddy-headed People con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, it is very high and dangerous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, to leave the whole buſineſs of their Salvation to God; and to throw it all upon God, firſt to ordain them peremtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Everlaſting Happineſs, and then to work upon them after an Irreſiſtible man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as if they were to be haled and forced to it, though with all their ill Qualities about them, and notwithſtanding their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs; in particular, than which nothing can be more Oppoſite to the Love of God, nor to the Condition of that Place, which is the Habitation of his Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:56573:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> That our Care muſt be, to make ſuch a due Uſe of Gods Love and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards us all, as to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thoſe things which are indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſibly neceſſary, in order to the actual Poſſeſſion of God's Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom. The Reaſon of this, and what the things are, which we are bound to perform.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> CONSIDERING therefore, what Qualifications are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in Us, to make our preſent Calling and Election firm, effectual, and eternally Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to us, our care muſt be in the fifth place, to make ſuch a due Uſe of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love, and Goodneſs towards us all; as to perform thoſe things which are indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſibly neceſſary, in order to the actual
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:56573:56"/>
Poſſeſſion of God's Everlaſting Kingdom. As yet, the way to it is laid open for us, and we have a Liberty and Power given us to enter in; but it is upon certain Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. We are delivered from a neceſſity of Periſhing, notwithſtanding our many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations; we are made capable of Eternal Life, notwithſtanding our former guilt: But yet, divers things are required on our part, that we may be actually admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fixt State of Happineſs in Heaven. Though God loved us, and gave his Son to us, to tender ſatisfaction in our ſtead, and by undergoing a Temporary Death himſelf, to Reſcue us from Everlaſting Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, (in which Services of the Divine Oeconomy, the World had not any the leaſt Hand; they were acts of pure Grace, of Mercy undeſerved, unthought of by Mankind) yet God being the Soveraign Governour and Legiſlator of the Univerſe, it would have been inconſiſtent with his Honour and Greatneſs, to have given up the Authority of his Laws, which yet he muſt have done, had he permitted us to take our own Courſes, and to live accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our own Wills, without any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Therefore, that he might at once provide for our Indemnity, and ſecure his own Authority alſo, when Chriſt was pleaſed ſo freely to undertake the Office
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:56573:56"/>
of a Mediator; it was Covenanted between the Father and Him, that upon ſuch and ſuch Conditions, his Obedience, Death and Interceſſion, ſhould be perfectly avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able on our behalf. And, for the making of thoſe terms good it was Covenanted likewiſe, that the Holy Spirit ſhould be given to inable us for the performance of thoſe Duties which were expected from us; and that ſuch a Meaſure ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted at our Hands, as we ſhould perform by our ſincere endeavours, according to our Capacities and Power. Hence it was, that Chriſt brought us Laws from Heaven, to Regulate and Govern our Actions; that we might not fruſtrate the Counſel and Love of God towards us, that we might not at laſt fail of God's Grace, nor come ſhort of his Glory; and of that Happineſs which the Lord Jeſus came into the World to purchaſe for us all. The Price is paid; and it was Love unſpeakable in Chriſt to lay it down, and in his Father to accept it at his Hands for us. But though the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Purchaſe be made yet, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Poſſeſſion of it, we muſt be careful to behave our ſelves ſo as God requires us, in order to the conveyance of the Title, to every particular Soul. We muſt believe ſtedfaſtly on the Name of the Son of God; and to this Faith, we muſt add ſincere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:56573:57"/>
from all Dead Works; and make it our buſineſs to ſerve God, in true Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Righteouſneſs, all the days of our Life. Without theſe Performances on our part, Chriſt will, in the end, profit us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe he is the <hi>Author of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation unto all them that obey him, Heb.</hi> 5. 9. They only will have the Final and Everlaſting enjoyment of God's Love to the World. For the Law, by which the Righteous Judge of all the Earth will proceed, is very plain, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>He will render to every Man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Deeds; to them, who by patient continuance in well-doing, ſeek for Glory, and Honour, and Immortality</hi> (God will render) <hi>Eternal Life: But unto them that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, and do not obey the Truth, but obey Unrighteouſneſs</hi> (He will render) <hi>Indignation and Wrath, Tribulation and Anguiſh upon every Soul that doeth Evil, of the</hi> Jew <hi>firſt, and alſo of the</hi> Gentile; <hi>But Glory, and Honour, and Peace, to every Man that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Good, to the</hi> Jew <hi>firſt, and alſo to the</hi> Gentile; <hi>for there is no reſpect of Perſons with God.</hi> You ſee, Men's Eternal Doom, depends upon the Quality of their Lives and Actions here; as they are either Good or Evil, ſo will God reward them with Happineſs, or Miſery hereafter. And for this Reaſon it was, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:56573:57"/>
God the Saviour of all Men, <hi>eſpecially of thoſe that believe,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 10. He is the Saviour of all Men Intentionally; becauſe, He intended not to Reject any by an Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Decree, or to exclude any from the Hopes and Means of Salvation; but, by the Doctrines and Holy Life of his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> did intend to open and ſhew the way of Peace unto all, and encouraged all People to follow it to the end; and becauſe too he ſent <hi>Chriſt</hi> to offer him ſatisfaction for the Sins of all Men, to Die for all Men, and to Merit Eternal Salvation for all, if all would lay hold on his Merits, by ſuch a lively, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, and purifying Faith, as is perfected by Charity. In ſhort, becauſe he hath done thoſe things which were becoming and proper for a Wiſe and Merciful God to do, for Sinful, and Reaſonable Creatures, in order to their Salvation: He is rightly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Saviour of all Men, Sufficiently, Meritoriouſly, Intentionally; and if he be not to all Actually and Effectually ſo too, it muſt proceed from the voluntary Neglect and Crimes of ſome, who by their Evil Deeds, hinder themſelves from being Actually and Effectually Saved. To Illuſtrate this by a plain Similitude (ſuch as it is:) Suppoſe a great number of us were Captives, and Bond Slaves, ſold (as Slaves were formerly wont to be Sold) into the Hands of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:56573:58"/>
and Mercileſs Maſters: And ſuppoſe the King of his tender Compaſſion and Goodneſs towards us, as having been his own Subjects, ſhould ſend a valuable Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and Ample Ranſom, with a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious purpoſe to Redeem us all without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, but with a <hi>Proviſo,</hi> and upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of our true Faith and Allegiance to him; though ſome out of a ſtrange Love of Slavery, or through Careleſneſs or Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Temper, or by ſome other Miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, might hinder themſelves from being Actually Ranſomed, and ſo throw away their Liberty for ever; yet this could be no diſparagement to the King's Clemency and Goodneſs: He would deſerve the Name of our common Redeemer nevertheleſs, the intentional Redeemer of us all; and I doubt not, but in ſuch a caſe, we ſhould all think it very Reaſonable for us to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Kindneſs intended for all. To apply this inſtance, and to uſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Expreſſions which relate unto it: We were all once ſold under Sin, become the Servants of Unrighteouſneſs, taken Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives by the Devil, who laid his ſnares for all Mankind. But God of his Mercy, ſent his <hi>Son</hi> into the World to recover us all out of the ſnare of the Devil; to lead Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Captive, to give himſelf a Ranſom for all, to Redeem us from all Iniquity, to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:56573:58"/>
deliver us from the Bondage of Corruption, into the glorious Liberty of the Children of God; that being made free from Sin, we might become Servants unto God, and have our Fruit unto Holineſs, and the end Everlaſting Life. Nothing can be clearer, than this is from the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> that God ſent his <hi>Son</hi> into the World to this end and purpoſe, and with this moſt gracious Intention; and for this Reaſon, the whole Race of Mankind ought with all Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart to acknowledge, and adore him as the Saviour of us all. If, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his tenders of Grace and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſome will be ſo wanting to their Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Intereſt, as to continue ſtill in Bondage, and to go on in their Wicked and Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Courſes, till they take their laſt Fortunes with the Devil and his Angels, from whoſe Power and Damnation they might have been delivered: This will be indeed an ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of their own Crimes, and Folly, and a demonſtration of the Divine Juſtice; but no Diminution at all of God's Love and Goodneſs, by the various acts, whereof he ſhews now his great and unwillingneſs to have any of us Periſh. And it ſhews the Reaſon, why the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>He is the Saviour, eſpecially of them that Believe,</hi> becauſe, though he be loving unto all, yet theſe make a ſpecial uſe of his general Love;
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:56573:59"/>
they walk worthy of their Vocation by their ſpecial Obedience; they order all Actions in ſpecial conformity to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and Laws; and ſo a ſpecial Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt's Merits is made unto Them, that he becomes Finally, and Effectually, and in the Event and Iſſue, the Saviour of them onely.</p>
               <p>It concerns us therefore as much as our Eternal Comforts amount to, to take great care of our Hearts and Actions; becauſe, whatever Notions ſome are willing to pleaſe their Fancies with, every ones Final State will be ſuitable to the Nature and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Works. To be Prying into, and to Depend on God's Secret Counſels, and at the ſame time to neglect ones own Life, is the ready way to a more fatal downfall, than His, who walks on, gazing upon the Stars, and preſently breaks his Neck by tumbling down a rugged Precipice. The Revealed things belong to us; and this is the Revelation, that <hi>If we will enter into Life, we muſt keep the Commandments,</hi> Mat. 19. 17. That <hi>in every Nation, he that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God, and worketh Righteouſneſs, is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of him,</hi> Act. 10. 35. That <hi>we muſt work out our Salvation with fear and Trembling,</hi> Phil. 2. 12. That <hi>we muſt not be conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this World, but be transformed by the renewing of our Minds,</hi> Rom. 12. 2.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:56573:59"/>
That <hi>we must cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the Fleſh and Spirit,</hi> 2 Cor. 7. 1. That <hi>we muſt be Holy in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Converſation, as He which hath called us is Holy,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 15. And that <hi>if God ſo Loved us, we ought alſo to Love one another,</hi> 1 Joh. 4. 11. Theſe things being ſo plain, the great buſineſs of our Life ſhould be, to let all empty Speculations go, and to Study the Practical Part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. For it is not our Opinions, but ſolid Piety and Vertue that will carry us out in the day of God. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O Man, what is good: And what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do Juſtly, and to love Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and to walk Humbly with thy God?</hi> Saith the Prophet, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6. 8. And to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe hath the Grace Grace of God, which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Salvation, appeared unto all Men? Why, <hi>That denying Ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts, we ſhould live Soberly, Righteouſly and Godly in this preſent World,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 12. If then we would anſwer the Love of God to us, ſo as to be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for it indeed, and to reap benefit by it Everlaſtingly; this is the true Way, <hi>viz.</hi> to be led by the Goodneſs of God unto Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to bring forth Fruits Meet for Repentance, to Eſchew Evil, to follow Peace and Holineſs, to have our Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Honeſt in the World, to do thoſe things
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:56573:60"/>
that are Juſt, and Pure, and Lovely, and of good Report; to ſerve God acceptably with Reverence and Godly Fear, to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all Bitterneſs, Malice and Hatred; to put on as the Elect of God, Bowels of Mercies, Kindneſs, Humbleneſs of Mind, Meekneſs, Long-ſuffering, forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any Man have a Quarrel againſt any; and over all to put on Charity, which is the Bond of Perfectneſs. Theſe are ſo many Branches of the whole Duty of Man; and if ye do theſe things, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Conceits uncharitable People may have of you, ye ſhall never fall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:56573:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> That we muſt make God all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Returns of love. What love is. How excellent when it is a Divine Affection. Two things ſhewed; <hi>Firſt,</hi> How we may Acquire the love of God. <hi>Secondly,</hi> How we are to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it; (<hi>viz</hi>) By Obeying him; by Reſembling him; and by deſiring the Preſent, and Future Fruition of him.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> TO diſpoſe our Minds through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for theſe Religious performances, we ſhould above all things poſſeſs our Hearts with ſuch a Senſe of God's Love to us, as will naturally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite us to return all poſſible degrees of Love to him. Love is a moſt vigorous Affection of the Soul, a Principle of Action, that Works and Exerts it Self
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:56573:61"/>
after an Omnipotent manner, as if it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled that miraculous Faith, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveth Mountains: Tis an Affection that bears up againſt all difficulties, that breaks thorough all Oppoſition, that ſpares no Coſt, that begrudgeth nothing, either of Time or Labour, and that engageth all the Faculties of the Soul, in ſuch gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Undertakings as Dull, Selfiſh, and Phlegmatick Natures, are hardly capable of opening a Thought to. In ſhort, it is ſuch a commanding Paſſion, as brings a Man into Captivity with his own Conſent, and makes him pleaſantly and chearfully a Vaſſal; witneſs that ſingle inſtance of Love, <hi>Jacob</hi> who notwithſtanding the unworthy Artifices of his Unkle <hi>Laban,</hi> looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his many Years Servitude, but as a few Days, for the Affection he bore to his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved <hi>Rachel, Gen.</hi> 29 As this Affection is more and more Purified, ſo it riſeth in its Vigor; and when it comes to be a Divine Love, placed upon God, and upon the Son of God, it is a moſt Active Delightful Principle of Obedience to his Will in all things. It is that which ſets the Bleſſed Angels upon the Wing, to Execute his Commands with ſuch Pleaſure and Alacrity. The ſame Divine Principle inſpired the Apoſtles, and other ſuch Saints of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (eſpecially in the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gining of <hi>Christianity</hi>) to Do,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:56573:61"/>
and to Suffer all that was poſſible for <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Name; with that Reſolution, Chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Zeal, which made them Renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto all Ages. <hi>The Love of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth us,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 14. And to omit other Inſtances, I cannot but remember here the Ardent Zeal of that famous imitator of St. <hi>Paul, Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the Martyr, Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> in the Apoſtolical Age; who being Condemn'd to be thrown to the Lyons, as he was on his tedious Journey to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he was to Suffer, he ſent before-hand to the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> there, an Epiſtle, wherein he moſt Importunately and Paſſionately deſired them, not to uſe any means in the World, to prevent his Martyrdom; but rather aſſiſt the earneſt Deſires he had to Die for the Lord <hi>Jeſus.</hi> He Prayed heartily, that it might be his Lot, to be torn in pieces by the Wild Beaſts, which were provided for him; and that he might find them Fierce and Ravenous. He profeſs'd, that (rather than fail) he would Court, nay Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them to Devour him: He expreſs'd his Wiſhes, that he might endure any Torments, the Flames, the Croſs the united Force of Savage Creatures, Manglings, Dilacerations, the diſperſing of his Bones, the chopping of all his Limbs into pieces, the Conſumption of his
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:56573:62"/>
whole Body, nay all the pains the Devil could bring upon him, ſo that he might but enjoy <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> He declared that all the Kingdoms of this World, would do him no good without Martyrdom; and that he had much rather Die for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to be with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> than be Monarch of the whole Earth; and the true cauſe of this his Flaming Zeal was, the great Senſe he had of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s wonderful Affection, in Dying for the World; which Commanded from him the return of theſe Paſſionate Affections to God and his Redeemer: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (ſaid he) my Love was Crucified.</p>
               <p>I have briefly obſerved theſe things to ſhew, that Love is a moſt powerful Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when it is Sincere, Hearty and Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. Of all the Affections of the Soul, it is that which will not be concealed, or lie idle. There is a vehemence in the Nature of it, which will break forth, and diſcover the Delights and Deſires that are within. And therefore to Fit and Temper our Minds duly for thoſe Performances which God looketh for, as a Genuine return on our part, for his abundant Love to us all; and as neceſſary means, in order to the Final and Everlaſting Fruition of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; we muſt raiſe our Affections to this
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:56573:62"/>
hihg and noble Pitch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to Love the Lord our God <hi>With all our Heart, and with all our Soul, and with all our Mind,</hi> Mat. 22. 37. Our Saviour there calls it the firſt and great Commandment, not only becauſe it is of prime Obligation, but moreover, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the main Genuine ſpring, whence all Acts of Obedience to God, do natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally flow.</p>
               <p>INDEED <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us. That <hi>the Fear of the Lord, is the beginning of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> Prov. 9. 10. And doubtleſs the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of God's Power and Juſtice, is a very neceſſary thing to keep People in Awe, nay the only thing that is a Check upon thoſe, who would not ſtick to commit Iniquity with greedineſs, and run out into all manner of Exceſſes, were it not for fear of God's Judgments in this World, and of Hell Torments in the next. But though this be a good reſtraint, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly needful in its kind, yet it is far from being ſo excellent a preſervative of Virtue and Religion, as the Love of God is. For this Fear is in ſome Men the Effect of an Abſurd, Slaviſh Diſpoſition, Proceeding purely from Self-Love, and from a Natural Principle of Self-Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; which makes them forbear thoſe Sins for their own ſakes only; which
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:56573:63"/>
otherwiſe they would readily Commit, were there no Danger: And as for thoſe poſitive Acts of Obedience, to the Divine Commands which they perform, they proceed too, from the ſame ſerviſe Principle; ſo that it is at beſt, a Forc'd and Unwilling Obedience, extorted meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Pacifie a terrible God, that is Arm'd with Power to Revenge the Contempt of of his moſt Sacred Authority: And tho' there is (and ought to be) in the very Beſt and moſt Holy People, a Fear of God, or a Dread of his Diſpleaſure, and of Eternal Puniſhment: A Fear that is well pleaſing unto God, and very uſeful to themſelves; yet in thoſe Pious Hearts, it is attended and mixed with a very Ardent Love; and ſo it is an Ingenuous Fear, a Filial Reverence, like that Awful Regard, which Dutiful and Affectionate Children have for their dear Parents; at the ſame time they are afraid of their Diſpleaſure, and Obey; but Obey with Chearfulneſs and Delight. It is Love (that moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Affection of the Soul) it is that which makes Fear ſuch a good and kindly Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Action; and the warmer our Love is, the more Extenſive, Hearty, and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable will our Obedience be. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we may Anſwer the Love of God to us, by a chearful performance of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:56573:63"/>
thoſe things, which of his great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Goodneſs he hath propoſed to our Practice, that thereby he may fit us for true Happineſs in Heaven; To Anſwer I ſay this his unſpeakable Love to us all, we ſhould uſe all poſſible endeavours, to Enflame our Souls with ſuch a Love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him again, as wrought ſo vigorouſly in the Saints of Old, who counted not their very Lives dear to them, <hi>So that they might finiſh their Courſe with Joy,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of himſelf, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 24.</p>
               <p>In the cloſing of this whole Subject, which began with the Contemplation of God's Love, and is now to end with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of ours: It will be requiſite for me to ſhew theſe two things,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> How we may acquire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> How we are to Expreſs that Divine Affection, which I now ſpeak of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly, Firſt then,</hi> The way to Acquire this Love is, to repreſent God to our Minds as the beſt of all Beings; and that in a two fold Reſpect.</p>
               <p>1. As the moſt Deſirable, Delightful, and Amiable good in his Nature; and,</p>
               <p>2. As a Being, that is, moſt Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative of Goodneſs, and Happineſs to us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1ſt. Firſt,</hi> We ſhould repreſent God to our Minds as the moſt Amiable Good in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:56573:64"/>
his Nature Some Perfections are very indear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Attractive of our Affections, tho' we be ſuppoſed to be never the better for them. As, that Perfection of Body, which conſiſteth in External Beauty, and Lovelineſs, inviteth the Spectators Affection, though the Perſon ſo Accompliſh'd is, and is ever like to be an utter Stranger to him. The Beauties of the Mind are much more At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive of a Rational Affection, Wiſdom, Truth, Sincerity, Faithfulneſs, Gentleneſs, Meekneſs, Patience, Righteouſneſs, Mercy, a Condeſcending Temper, and whatever comes under the notion of true Goodneſs; theſe are Amiable Vertues, and Diſpoſitions, which we cannot but Love one another for, though they are in us but in a ſcanty Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and are mixed too with many Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Such as they be, they are Derived alſo: We are beholding for them to that Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream and firſt Cauſe, who is the Fountain of all Excellencies; and therefore they muſt needs be moſt Amiable in God, becauſe in Him they are Abſolute and Infinite; nor can we conceive any Perfections Intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, or Moral, in the moſt Excellent Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, no not in the Bleſſed Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but what are tranſcendently Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the Father of Spirits, whoſe Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies admit of no boundaries, or Abatement. Therefore to kindle and maintain in our
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:56573:64"/>
Hearts, a Rational, Holy and Divine Love, we ſhould repreſent God to our Minds un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch charming <hi>Ideas,</hi> as become a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo admirably Perfect in himſelf, ſo Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendently, and Gloriouſly Excellent. We ſhould Conceive of him, as a Being that knoweth how to order all things for the beſt, and with a ſtrict regard to the good of his whole Creation, and of every part of it, that is but capable of participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his Goodneſs: As a Being that taketh a Particular care of Mankind; and more eſpecially of thoſe Men, who Study to live in conformity to his Laws; as a Being that is always ſteddy and conſtant to his Promiſes, nor is capable of Lying (a thing ſo Repugnant to his moſt Bleſſed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; that none but the Devil can be the Father of it:) As a Being that is Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in all his ways, that loveth Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and hateth Iniquity, that giveth Laws which are Juſt and Good, that rewardeth every one according to his Works, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth none but according to Equity and Eternal Reaſon. We ſhould Conceive of him as a Being, that is ready to take Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion upon all that need it, and are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his Mercies; that is, unwilling to have any of us Loſt, that is, ſlow to Anger, that is, patient towards all, that is, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, Gracious, Long-ſuffering, abundant
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:56573:65"/>
in Goodneſs and Truth, keeping Mercy for Thouſands, forgiving Iniquity, Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Sin. In ſhort, we ſhould Conceive of God as a bleſſed Being, that loveth and careth for our poor Souls, Infinitely, more than we our ſelves do. Under theſe lovely <hi>Ideas,</hi> God repreſenteth himſelf in the Holy Scriptures; and to behold him under ſuch raviſhing Conceptions, is an effectual way of raiſing in us a Rational affection to him; becauſe one great Branch of Love conſiſteth in Eſteem; in that Honour and Admiration which ſprings from the Excellencies we Diſcern, or believe to be in the Object of our Affections.</p>
               <p>2. ANOTHER Branch of it is, the placing of our Hearts upon the Object we highly Admire; the deſiring and Seeking after it, and delighting in it, as the precious and dear thing, wherein we conceive our Happineſs to be Lodged. And to raiſe our Affections to this noble pitch, we ſhould repreſent God to our Minds alſo as a Being, that is actually Communicative of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Happineſs to us. Love naturally commandeth Love again: 'Tis an Affection of the Soul that cannot reſiſt any thing which is like it ſelf; but preſently cloſeth with the object, that by ſuitable expreſſions of Kindneſs invites and meets it. Here
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:56573:65"/>
then we ſhould conſider, how that moſt perfect and excellent Being hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand with us, what good he hath done us, and doth do for us daily. The Life we now live, and are ſo very tender of, was given us at the firſt by that Father of Spirits, and is every Moment ſupported by his ſole Providence which Feeds and Cloaths us, and hath Preſerved us all along from innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Dangers; from many which Time may have worn out of our Memories; and from more, which we have not minded, or were ſo hidden that we could not diſcover them. Thoſe Bleſſings which lie in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to Mankind, every one hath had his ſhare of: And were particular Perſons ſo advertent as to obſerve God's particular Providence to them, there is not one in the World but would find himſelf obliged to make God particular returns of Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Affection. God is ſo Good to the meaneſt and moſt Ungrateful People, that if every one would but keep by him two private Regiſters, one of God's Mercies, and another of his own Actions, the very ſenſe of God's Goodneſs to every Man (I mean as to the things of this Life) could not but warm all our Hearts towards him, eſpecially if we did open both Regiſters, and then fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compare, what we have had, with what we have deſerv'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:56573:66"/>BUT above all we ſhould conſider, what God hath done for our Immortal Souls, by his wiſe and gracious ordering all things that relate to a Life Eternal. That State being Everlaſtingly Unchangeable, when once Men enter into it, whether it be a State of Bleſſedneſs, or Torments, God of his Infinite Goodneſs, and moſt tender Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, was pleaſed to make ſuch ample Proviſion for the well-fare of us all, that one might think it hardly poſſible for Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Probity and Thoughtfulneſs to miſs of a Bleſſed Eternity. He ſent the Son of his Love to tranſact the weighty buſineſs of a Mediator, that God and Men might be no longer at a diſtance. The Lord Jeſus did innumerable Miracles, to prove and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm his Divine Authority: He declared unto the World the whole Counſel of God, that nothing of Light might be wanting: He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd us ſuch Precepts as are ſuitable to our own Reaſon, and ſuch as are Eaſie and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful to thoſe, who will but Accuſtom themſelves to the obſervation of them: He hath encouraged us with ſuch Promiſes, as are enough to Animate us in the greateſt Difficulties, and to carry us undauntedly through all. He ſubmitted to a moſt Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Reproachful Death, that he might offer up a full, perfect, and ſufficent Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:56573:66"/>
Sacrifice, and Satisfaction for the ſins of the whole World, and that in Vertue of his Death, he might for ever make Interceſſion for us. He gave his Holy Spirit to inſpire his Apoſtles, and to aſſiſt us all, by ſuch kindly Operations as are ſuitable to Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, endued with Rational faculties, to Illuminate our Underſtandings, to perſwade our Wills to purifie our Affections, to ſtrengthen our Hopes, and to Comfort and Cheriſh us in our Trials. He wooeth us daily by his Ambaſſadors, who beſeech us in Chriſt's ſtead, that we would be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto God. He hath inſtituted Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, to Seal the Mercies of God to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular Soul, which will uſe thoſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances in a due manner. In ſhort, he hath afforded us all the means, which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and Immortal Souls ſtand in need of; and all this for no other end, but to make us Eternally Happy; happy in the fruition of Himſelf, who is ſo infinitely Happy in his own Perfections and Condition, that he needeth not the Service or Attendance of Men, or of Angels. Theſe things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could not flow from any other Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but a Principle of Goodneſs. And this is the true genuine Reaſon of Love; whereas thoſe frightful <hi>Ideas,</hi> under which ſome have miſrepreſented the moſt Bleſſed God, ſerve to caſt a Damp on Men's Spirits,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:56573:67"/>
and to Alienate their Minds and Affections from that Divine and moſt Amiable Being. <q>
                     <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Book of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> deſcribes thoſe People as God's Enemies, and their own too, who think hardly of God, and believe him to be Fierce, Falſe, Muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Revengeful, Cruel, Angry upon every light occaſion, Auſtere, Rigorous and Hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. He tells us there, that of all Men, ſuch are in the very worſt condition, that they are Afraid of him, even when they have Recourſe to him; that they Reproach at the ſame time and Flatter him; that they Pray to him, and in the ſame Breath Aſperſe him; that at once they Fear him, and Hate him; and that though they go to his Temples to Worſhip, and to offer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices to him, yet this is ſuch a ſort of Courtſhip, wherewith Flatterers accoſt Tyrants they Hate, and Curſe them in their Hearts, the very time they ſeem to Honour them.</q> 
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> thought all fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Ideas</hi> to be unſuitable to the Nature of a Deity. <q>God (ſaith he) is the Hope of Vertue, not a Formidable, Dreadful ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Though Artificers are wont to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent him by Images that have a terrible Aſpect, yet Philoſophers will tell you, that God's Majeſty is attended with Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with Benignity, with a kind and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Providence.</q> And he was of <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:56573:67"/>
his Mind (how ſlightly ſoever ſome thought of it) <q>That wiſe and Vertuous Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are in the beſt Temper, when they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto God, becauſe their Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are mixt with fair Opinions of him, and with ſincere Affections towards him.</q> Theſe, you will think, were great things for an Heathen to ſay, and ſo they were. But we find by conſtant Experience, that 'tis natural for us to Hate thoſe we are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of, and Nature will work after the ſame manner, when we have to do with God, if we conceive of him under ſuch ſcaring notions, as to believe him to be a Sowre, Harſh. Angry, and Tyrannical Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Such Qualities are very Hateful; they create Horror and Averſion, but 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to beget any Love; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt be utterly incompatible with the Glories and Excellencies of God, whoſe Mercy is over all his Works, and who ſheweth his Almighty Power moſt chiefly, by doing works of Pity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and to entertain ſuch apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of him, as are a diſparagement to his great Goodneſs, is the ready way to bring us to the condition of thoſe old Pagans, who Worſhip'd Evil <hi>Doemons,</hi> meerly for Fear, leſt they ſhould Hurt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:56573:68"/>I deny not, but there may be ſome Kind and Meaſure of Love in thoſe, who look upon God as a ſtern and rigorous Being, if they can but perſwade themſelves into a Belief, that God is ſo Partial to Their Souls, as to make them his particular Favourites by a fixt and unconditional Decree. But this degree and ſort of Love, is meerly a Paſſion of the Senſitive Soul, raiſed by the power of Fancy; becauſe the Belief of this abſolute purpoſe towards Them, in particular, wanteth the Authority of Divine Revelation. Rational Affection, or that Love towards God which is neceſſary to make all our performances a reaſonable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, is quite another thing. It is a fervour of Heart, excited by the rational Faculty, the Underſtanding, upon full and clear Conviction of the Mind out of the Word of God; which Conviction is wrought by the frequent Account we find in the Holy Scriptures, touching the intrinſick Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Goodneſs of God's Nature, and touching his great Love and relative Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards all Mankind: This is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, true Ground of that Divine Love I have ſpoken of, and Ardent and Genuine affection of the Heart, which the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God's Univerſal Goodneſs, is apt to kindle in the Soul of every Man, who
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:56573:68"/>
is not conſcious of any willful and groſs Wickedneſs, which maketh him afraid of the Juſtice of God.</p>
               <p>AS far as Nature could help them, the wiſer and more conſiderate Heathens attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Love of God, by thoſe weak diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries they had of the Divine Goodneſs. There are (ſays <hi>Seneca, de Ira, lib. 2. cap.</hi> 27.) <q>Some things which cannot Hurt, they are ſo Beneficent and Succouring in their Nature, as the immortal Gods, which neither will, nor can be Miſchievous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Nature is Mild and Gentle.</q> He ſpeaks in the <hi>Plural Number,</hi> to gratifie the Humour of thoſe Times; but he means, that one Supream God, whom the more Intelligent <hi>Pagans</hi> Worſhipp'd; nay, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd with Affection; as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where (<hi>de Benef. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.) <q>No Man in his right Senſes will be horribly afraid of God, becauſe it is madneſs to Dread that which is Beneficial, nor can any Man Love that object, which they Fear after that manner.</q> Accordingly <hi>Maximus Tyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> tells us, <q>That the truly Religious Man is the Friend of God, or one that loves God, and that he is therefore Happy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is a lover of God, (<hi>Diſſert.</hi> 4.)</q> Such conſiderable Notions thoſe obſerving Men had of the Goodneſs of God, as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:56573:69"/>
produced great Affection to him. And if we Chriſtians, who have, beſides the Book of <hi>Nature,</hi> the Divine Writings, would but attentively conſider, by what we read in them, what a great lover of Souls that moſt Perfect Being is, and what various Methods he hath uſed to ſave all our Souls from Periſhing Everlaſtingly, it would be the moſt Aſtoniſhing thing in the World, if ſuch conſiderations did not render him the moſt indearing Object, ſince the very <hi>Publicans</hi> loved thoſe who loved them; nay, ſince the very Ox knoweth his Owner, and the Aſs his Maſter's Cribb.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> HAVING thus ſhewed the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per way of Acquiring the Love of God; I proceed now to conſider how we are to Expreſs it. And that our Practice as to this may be Regular; we muſt note (what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is clear to all Men from the natural Operations of this Affection) that Love excites us powerfully to theſe three Things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1ſt,</hi> To obſerve the Will.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2dly,</hi> To reſemble the Temper: And,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3dly,</hi> To deſire the Fruition of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, we have an Ardent Affection for.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:56573:69"/>FIRST, True Love makes us obſerve ones Pleaſure, ſeeing this Affection is made up of Eſteem and Honour in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of Complacency in the Heart, a ready Compliance of the Will muſt be the next thing; becauſe, this is only the Paying of that Deference which we Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be Due; and an Act of Reſpect, whereby we are willing and delighted to Oblige. In all Caſes it makes us to be yielding: But when it comes to be a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love, and hath the Bleſſed God for its Object, it cannot but engage us to Entire and Univerſal Obedience, becauſe the Soul hath God's Soveraign Authority in its Eye, beſides thoſe Beauties and Excellencies of his Nature, which are ſo Amiable, and ſo Powerful in their Influence: God being the ſole Governour of the World, that hath a right to give Laws to our Souls, and a Power to Diſpoſe of them, we are indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fibly Obliged to make his Will (when once it is Revealed) the Rule and Meaſure of our Actions. And the Neceſſity of this adds a mighty force to thoſe Inclinations, which Love alone createth evermore in the Mind, to claſp with his Holy and Righteous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts. Hence it is, that the Scripture in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprets Obedience, as the only Sign and Argument of a Divine Love. <hi>I will ſhew
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:56573:70"/>
Mercy unto Thouſands of them that Love me, and keep my Commandments,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 6. <hi>If ye Love me, keep my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Job.</hi> 14. 15. <hi>This is the Love of God, that we keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> ſaith the Divine Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 3.</p>
               <p>THIS then is the firſt way of Expreſſing our Affections towards God, in return of his great Love and Goodneſs to us, and to all Mankind, by Doing all things he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of us, with a ready and chearful Mind. It is not a ſtarch'd Geſture, nor a Formal carriage, nor an External Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor a wateriſh Look, nor a furious Zeal for dry Opinions; it is not theſe, or any of theſe things, that is the Sign of that Divine Love, which is the Noble Principle of Religion. For theſe outward ſhews may be conſiſtent with the Hatred of God and Man; and then they are only ſo many Gloſſes of Hypocrites, void of that Rational and Generous Affection, which God's Love calls for. 'Tis the entire ſubjection of the Heart, Operating, and Exerting all its Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, by Religious, Sober, Honeſt, and Charitable Actions: 'Tis the ſubduing our unreaſonable Paſſions, the denying all Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs and Worldly Luſts, the cleanſing of our ſelves from all filthineſs of Fleſh and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:56573:70"/>
Spirit, the ſquaring of our Lives according to the Laws of God: To this Pliant and Obediential frame of Soul, that is the true Teſtimony and Fruit of that Love, which God looks for, and which is in the Sight of God of ſo great a Price. We muſt call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him daily with Faithful and Enflamed Spirits; we muſt apply our Hearts to the Study and Practice of Religion; we muſt do Juſtly, Love Mercy, and walk humbly with our God; we muſt be ſincere, and without any Guile, and deal truly with all Men, as in the preſence of God; we muſt Love one another, and Forgive one another, <hi>For he that loveth not his Brother, whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen?</hi> 1 Joh. 4. 20. In ſhort, to expreſs our Love of God after a right manner, we muſt obey him in all things; and that, with enlarged Hearts, with Filial Reverence, with Ingenuous Dutifulneſs, with a ready Will, and with ſuch Alacrity, Chearfulneſs, and Pleaſure of Mind, as becometh thoſe, for whom God hath been pleaſed to do ſo many Miracles of Mercy.</p>
               <p>SECONDLY, Another proper Act of Love, is, to Study Imitation. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a Twofold Cauſe, partly from the great Value we have of, and the great Complacency we take in the Object of our
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:56573:71"/>
Affections, which being ſo Amiable in our Eye, doth naturally Excite us to transform our ſelves into a Similitude of it. And partly it proceeds from an innate Deſire we all have of being Beloved again, which being impracticable without an Harmony of Mind and Temper between both Parties, it is neceſſary for the one (that Love may be Reciprocal) to ſuit himſelf to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the other; eſpecially, if that other be a Superior in Dignity, Excellence, and Perfection. Conſidering therefore that God is infinitely the moſt Excellent, the moſt Excellent and Perfect of all Beings, the Love which ſprings from a Senſe of his Perfections, and reacheth after a Plenary Communication of them, muſt needs Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulate ones Soul to put on a Diſpoſition (as far as 'tis poſſible) agreeable to the Mind and Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>THEREFORE, that we may Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Eminently expreſs our Love to God; we muſt by all means endeavour to reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him, I mean, in all thoſe things that are Imitable by us. We muſt be ſincere in Heart, as that moſt Bleſſed Being is. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the capacities and Powers of our Nature, we muſt be Holy and Separate from all Moral Impurities, as God is; we muſt be Patient, Long-ſuffering, and ſlow
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:56573:71"/>
to Anger, as He is; we muſt be Treatable and Reconcilable, notwithſtanding all Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts and Injuries, as he is; we muſt be ſtrict Obſervers of the Eternal Rules of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and Juſtice, as He is; we muſt be Steaddy and True to all our Promiſes, as the Faithful God is; we muſt be Merciful and Benign, Compaſſionate and Tender-hearted, Bountiful and Impartial, Kind and Good to all Men, even to our Enemies, as that Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and Beneficent Being is, who maketh his <hi>Sun</hi> to ſhine upon the Good and upon the Evil too, and ſendeth his Rain upon the Juſt, and upon the Unjuſt alſo. Thoſe Ill-natured People, who are Uncharitable, Rigid, Fierce, Implacable, Auſtere, Cruel, Revengeful, and Outragious, ſhould look upon God's Glories, the Perfections, and Beauties of his Nature, and ſhould employ their time upon this great Study, how to be like God, according to thoſe charming <hi>Ideas,</hi> under which He is repreſented unto us in the Holy Scriptures. <hi>Thou thoughteſt Wickedly, that I am even ſuch a one as thy ſelf</hi> (ſaith God,) <hi>but I will reprove thee, and ſet before thee, the things that thou haſt done,</hi> Pſal. 50. 21. God will not be ſerved with our Vices, nor muſt we be ſuch Fools as to think we love him, by entitling him to the Filth and Refuſe of our Corrupt Nature. Goodneſs, is ſo bright a Beam of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:56573:72"/>
the Divine Glory, and ſo eaſie to be ſeen in every part of the Creation, that Men cannot but diſcover it by the Eye of Common, Natural Reaſon. The old <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> Admired it, and believed God to be the Beſt Being; and therefore Ador'd him, Prayed to him in all their Straits, and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, and Celebrated his Praiſes as well as Nature could teach them: For which U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Cuſtom amongſt all Mankind, there could not have been any ſufficient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, had they not Univerſally Believed, not only the Exiſtence of a Deity; but moreover, that the Divine Being is a God of Power, and a God of great Clemency, Benignity, and Goodneſs. This was the true Ground of their Religious Offices, and of that Love, which Nature wrought in their Hearts towards him. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any of us Chriſtians may talk of our Loving God, all is but Froth and Vanity, Senſeleſs and Ridiculous Profeſſion, unleſs we reſemble him in Goodneſs, <hi>Be ye Merciful even as your Father is Merciful,</hi> as our Bleſſed Saviour ſaid, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. 36.</p>
               <p>THIRDLY, And Laſtly, to expreſs our Love towards God, we muſt earneſtly deſire the Fruition of him. This every one ſeeth to be another natural Act of this Affection, and the moſt Vehement
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:56573:72"/>
Effort of it, to be United to its Object, and to have it in actual Poſſeſſion; and the Reaſon is, becauſe Happineſs is Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended to conſiſt in ſuch Enjoyment. Now God being the true Felicity of the Soul, the only proper Object which the Faculties of the Soul can be Employed upon with ſatisfaction, and which can ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Anſwer all our Deſires, it is impoſſible to Conceive, how we can truly Love him, eſpecially under the notion of our Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without Ardent, and Impatient Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings after the Fruition of him.</p>
               <p>THIS being ſo clear, the next thing we are to Note, is, that there is a Preſent, and a Future Fruition of God. The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Fruition, in reſpect of Degree, is very Imperfect, becauſe, we are yet in an Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect State; but in reſpect of Quality and Kind, is the ſame with that which is yet to come. For it conſiſteth in Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating God according to our Capacities, in Admiring the Perfections of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Majeſty, in ſetting our Hearts on him, as our Supream Good, in feeding our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires with the Raviſhing <hi>Ideas</hi> of him, in Delighting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and being highly pleaſed with the Senſe of him, and in ſuch other Beatifical Acts which are anſwerable to Rational Appetites. Every Divine Lover
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:56573:73"/>
hath ſomething of all this in this Preſent Imperfect State; 'tis the Fruition which now Crowneth our Affections, that Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Fellowſhip of Communion with God, which we enjoy in this Life. To Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs therefore our Love to him in this reſpect, we ſhould have him always in our Minds, be full of worthy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of him, and make the thoughts of his Glorious Eſſence and Attributes to dwell in our Hearts daily. We ſhould Exalt him in our Minds above all things, and make our Souls ſenſible, that we have none in Heaven but Him, none upon Earth, to be deſired in Compariſon of Him. We ſhould take Pleaſure in Divine Contemplations, and endeavour conſtantly to Satiate our Souls more and more with Delights of that Nature. We ſhould every day poſſeſs our Hearts with ſuch Affecting Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations as Theſe:</p>
               <p>O God! How Excellent is thy Name! How Radiant is thy Glory! How Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable are thy Perfections! How Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful are thy Works! How Beautiful are all thy Ways! How Righteous are thy Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons! How Equal are thy Commands! How Precious and Sweet are thy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes! How Infinite is thy Goodneſs!
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:56573:73"/>
How Aſtoniſhing are thy Mercies! How Charming is thy Love! How Helpfull and Saving is thy Power! How Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is thy Pity! How Bleſſed and Praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and Deſirable art Thou, O Thou great Lover of Souls, and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the World. To kindle in us! ſuch a Divine Flame, and to raiſe our Deſires ſtill, touching the Fruition of God, we ſhould Form our Hearts into a <hi>Devout</hi> Temper; give our Selves to Prayer, and to the Love of it daily. Inſenſate and Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs People, know not the Comforts, the Pleaſures, the Divine Enjoyments, which Tranſport the Minds of thoſe, who Pray to God with Stay'd, Fervent, and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Hearts. Certainly what Happineſs there is here below, Men of Holy, Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Devout Spirits have it: And that our Fruitions thereby may be the greater, and the more deſirable, we ſhould evermore be mindful of Publick and Solemn Devotion: Chiefly when Two or Three are gathered together in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Name, then is he in the midſt of us, and then is God with us; then we Enjoy him in a more eſpecial manner and meaſure; in the Congregation, in the Aſſembly of the Saints, in his Houſe of Prayer: There he ſcatters his Bleſſings, there he gives us participations of himſelf; there
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:56573:74"/>
he refreſheth us with a portion of thoſe Pleaſures, which are at his Right Hand. And this was the Reaſon of thoſe Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Wiſhes, Groans and Longings of the Holy Pſalmiſt, which upon the like occaſions, we ſhould be full of too: <hi>My Heart is fixed, O God, my Heart is fixed: I will Sing and give Praiſe. Awake up my Glory, I will go into this Sanctuary, and fall low on my Knees at thy Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool. Like as the Heart deſireth the Water-brooks, ſo longeth my Soul after Thee, O God. My Soul is a Thirſt for God, yea even for the Living God: When ſhall I come to appear before the Preſence of God! O How Amiable are thy Dwellings, O Lord of Hoſts! My Soul hath a Deſire and longing to enter into the Courts of the Lord; for one Day in thy Courts, is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a Thouſand: I had rather be a Door-keeper in the Houſe of my God, than to dwell in the Tents of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſee how paſſionate that good Man's Love to God was, though for the preſent Fruition of him. And if the Gleanings of the Grapes be ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable, what is the whole Vintage? I mean, that abundant and Eternal Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is Reſerved for us, till
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:56573:74"/>
that Day, when we ſhall have duly trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted all our Services here, and ſhall paſs from theſe Houſes of Prayer, into that Building of God, not made with Hands, the Everlaſting Habitation of his Glory.</p>
               <p>This Future Everlaſting Fruition of God ought to be the chief Object of our Deſires, becauſe it is our higheſt good; and becauſe it is the Ultimate end of the Divine Oeconomy, and of all our Labours of Love in this World.</p>
               <p>It is impoſſible for us truly and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to Love God, and not to groan within our Selves, whileſt we wait for this laſt Adoption; the Redemption of our Bodies, that we may be Cloathed upon all over with Immortality, and have theſe our vile Bodies changed, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned like unto <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s own Glorious Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that we may be in every Reſpect, fit to be with that great Lover of our Souls; and when we ſee him, may rejoyce with him, and with a joy like unto his, when after all the Ignominy and Torments of the Croſs, he had this moſt Comfortable Reflection, <hi>It is Finiſhed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:56573:75"/>
               <head>PRAYERS.</head>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <p>OLord, who never faileſt to help and govern them, whom thou doſt bring up in thy Sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt Fear and Love, Keep us, we Beſeech Thee, under the Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy good Providence, and make us to have a perpetual Fear and Love of thy Holy Name; through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:56573:75"/>
                  <p>OGod, who, haſt prepared for them that Love Thee ſuch good things as paſs Man's Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Pour into our Hearts, ſuch Love towards Thee, that we loving Thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, may obtain thy Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which exceed all that we can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <p>ALmighty and Everlaſting God, who hateſt nothing that Thou haſt made, and doſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give the Sins of all them that are Penitent: Create and make in us New and Contrite Hearts, that we Worthily lamenting our Sins, and acknowledging our Wretchedneſs; may
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:56573:76"/>
Obtain of Thee (the God of all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) perfect Remiſſion and Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <p>OAlmighty God, who alone canſt Order the Unruly Wills and Affections of Sinful Men; grant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy People, that they may Love the thing which thou Commandeſt, and deſire that which thou doſt Promiſe; that ſo among the ſundry, and manifold Changes of the World, our Hearts may ſurely There be fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed where true joys are to be found, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> Our Lord.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:56573:76"/>
                  <p>GRant We beſeech Thee, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, That like as We do Believe thy only Begotten Son our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to have Aſcended into the Heavens; So We may alſo in Heart and Mind, thither Aſcend, and with Him continually dwell, who liveth, and raigneth with Thee, and the Holy Ghoſt, one God, World without End.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:56573:77"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>W. Crook.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Practical Diſcourſe upon the Bleſſed Sacrament, ſhewing the Duties of the Communicant before, at, and after the <hi>Euchariſt. Octavo. Price 3s. 6d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A Practical Diſcourſe upon Prayer, in <hi>Octavo, Price Is.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. A Practical Diſcourſe upon Charity in its ſeveral Branches; and of the Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs and Uſeful Nature of this great <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Vertue. <hi>Octavo. Price 3s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Theſe three are alſo Bound together, having the Title of Dr.</hi> Pelling's Three Practical Diſcourſes. Vol. 1. Price <hi>6s. together.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. A Practical Diſcourſe upon Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wherein is ſhewn the Nature, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs and Uſefulneſs thereof, together with the ways of Expreſſing and Increaſing of it. <hi>Price 2s. 6d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>All Written by the Reverend Dr.</hi> Pelling, <hi>Author of this Book.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:56573:77"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
